<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The catechist catechized, or, An examination of an Anabaptistical catechism pretended to be published for the satisfaction and information of the people of God in Lancashire &amp;c. : also some observations both old and new concerning the pretended visibility ... of the present Roman Church and religion / sent to a gentleman upon his revolt to popery and now published for the churches good by Richard Hollingworth.</title>
            <author>Hollingworth, Richard, 1607-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44213</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2487</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28107</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10409793</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10409793</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44967</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44213)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44967)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1386:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The catechist catechized, or, An examination of an Anabaptistical catechism pretended to be published for the satisfaction and information of the people of God in Lancashire &amp;c. : also some observations both old and new concerning the pretended visibility ... of the present Roman Church and religion / sent to a gentleman upon his revolt to popery and now published for the churches good by Richard Hollingworth.</title>
                  <author>Hollingworth, Richard, 1607-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 51 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.M. for Luke Fawn,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anabaptists --  England --  Catechisms.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  England.</term>
               <term>Anabaptists --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44967:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44967:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Catechiſt Catechized: OR, AN EXAMINATION OF AN <hi>Anabaptistical Catechiſm,</hi> Pretended to be Publiſhed for the Satisfaction and Information of the People of God in <hi>Lancaſhire, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ALSO SOME OBSERVATIONS Both Old and New, Concerning the pretended Viſibility, Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality, Antiquity, Infallibility, Unity and Purity of the preſent <hi>Roman</hi> Church and Religion.</p>
            <p>Sent to a Gentleman upon his revolt to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, and now publiſhed for the Churches good.</p>
            <p>By RICHARD HOLLINVVORTH, <hi>Mancunienſ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for <hi>Luke Fawn,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the Parrot in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:44967:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44967:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is an <hi>Anabaptiſticall Catechiſm</hi> that walks abroad, lately directed to <hi>Lancaſhire;</hi> when it is of age and can anſwer for it ſelf you ſhal know the name of it; it is but newly brought forth to this County, and therefore not Chriſtned. If you meet with it, it would be a good work to <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> in which you dwel, to the Town of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> the place of your Nativity and Miniſtry, to make ſome Annotations of it; a few ſmooth ſtones out of ſoft <hi>Siloam</hi> hurl'd out of your ſling might lay it dead; a friendly arrow ſhot beyond it, may give warning that there is danger: I would not engage you to the conteſt with this <hi>A. B. C.</hi> but that Error is a ſpringing Leproſie in contagious times: Wormes in children may turn to the Plague: a few vacant hours will ſerve the buſineſs, and ſatisfie the earneſt deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Sir, Your Brother and fellow-Labourer in the Work of Chriſt,</hi> Richard Heyricke.</signed>
               <date>January <hi>1.</hi> — <hi>52.</hi>
               </date>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>For Mr. Richard Hollinworth, with my Love, Theſe.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:44967:3"/>
            <head>To all in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> that love and ſeek the Lord in all his Soul-filling Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, eſpecially them of the aſſociated Churches about MANCHESTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dearly Beloved, and longed for, our Joy and Crown;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu ſhall with more praiſe to God, light and ſtability to your ſelves, read the enſuing Treatiſe, if you firſt conſider, and lament, that (for abuſe of Ordinances) Satan, transforming himſelf into an Angel of Light, hath undermined all Ordinances of divine Light and Life: The Lords-Day not moral, publique ſolemn Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies turned into Houſe-meetings, publique Miniſtry exchanged for private Conferences, publique preaching of the Word common to gifted Brethren with called Miniſters; no prayer but when the Spirit moves, no communion in the Supper, but in Churches new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gathered, and no Baptiſm for Infants. No wonder if religious Ordinances be thus undermined, when the Doctrine of the holy Trinity, the Deity of Jeſus Chriſt, and of the Holy Ghoſt, the divine Authority of the Scriptures, the Obligation of the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, and other Fundamentals of Faith, Holineſs and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, are, by the Miniſters of the Prince of Darkneſs, profeſſedly overturned. No wonder that Children are unchurched, when ſo many Churches are unchurched, many of them that have done the former having begun at the latter. They who would not be ſaved by Ordinances, ſhall periſh for want of Ordinances; and they that would not unite themſelves to the Fountain of Life by Faith, ſhall be ſeparated from the ſtreams and conveyances of Life, that they may apparantly wither and dye: only, upon the living in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that by the ſubtilty of deluſion, or power of intereſt, are darkened and benummed, pray and weep, that the Sun of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs may ariſe, with healing in his wings. But the Ordinances being the purchaſe of Chriſts blood, as well as the Church, the gifts
<pb facs="tcp:44967:3"/>of his Princely Government, the Enſigns of his Victory over the Kingdom of Darkneſs, and of his glorious Aſcenſion, he will by his ſoveraign Power maintain; And to that end ſucceſſively enoble the ſpirits of ſome with beams of heavenly light and courage, that they ſhall diſcover the ſtratagems of Oppoſers, and adventure upon their Armies marſhalled againſt them, and triumphantly overcome by his glorious power, redeeming the captived Ordinances of their King unto a juſt and glorious Liberty. This being ſo high a favor from Chriſt, the glory of his Grace and Power, it is moſt thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to be accepted, and his Inſtruments to be had in honor, by all that rejoyce in the glory of his Kingdom. His Miniſters he hath deſigned to be the Executors of his laſt Will and Teſtament, to them it belongs by divine appointment, to give out the ſeveral Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacies there bequeathed, and to put in ſuit all them, in the high Court of ſacred Scripture, who ſhall, upon any pretence whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, detain any Legacy bequeathed; and where will their faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs more appear, then to open their mouth for the dumb, and to ſue for Childrens rights, whil'ſt they are forcibly wronged, and unable to right themſelves? where is greater Truſt, and more ſhining Fidelity? The right of Infants to Baptiſm hath of late been openly impleaded in reference to <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> and the Bill printed to be publiſhed there in ſpecial, with expectation of the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the godly; but, bleſſed be God, one of the Lords Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors (in <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> where part-taking was moſt deſired and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected) hath wiſely and faithfully joyned iſſue, and by clear Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath procured a determinate ſentence for the ſetling of their undoubted right upon Infants, to our great comfort, and the honor of the Kingdom of Chriſt, in the Right whereof Infants are right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly baptized. And our hope in the Lord Jeſus is, that the queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Right of Infants, and the ſhaking of their title, will have that influence upon all the godly in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> eſpecially Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents (peculiarly in <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> and the reſt of the aſſociated Churches) that out of enflamed love to Chriſt, and the Souls of their Children, they will ſo much the more ſettle their Judgments in this Truth, by the conſcionable and diligent uſe of this h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lp, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided by the Lord amongſt them, ſo ſeaſonably in reſpect of danger, and ſo ſuitably, in reſpect of clearneſs, brevity, and charge; that will happily lead to the believing, repenting, and prayerful uſe of this Ordinance, which is the Covenant-way of conveying to their
<pb facs="tcp:44967:4"/>Children the ſure and ſaving Mercies of the Covenant: ſo ſhall they, and others, who have ſeen the holy Seal ſet on in Infancy, clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly behold, in their holy life, the lively characters of the Spirit of the Covenant, the Image of the Lord Jeſus in their riper years; To their own abundant ſatisfaction, the ſilencing of Adverſaries, the increaſe of the Church myſtical, the encouragement of them that have carefully and painfully pleaded their Right; and above all, the honor of the Lord Jeſus, who in their Infancy opened unto them his Arms and Boſom in his Church, that in an hidden way he might warm them with a ſpiritual Life, to be manifeſted in due time. In this hope we pray for you, and labor amongſt you, that we might preſent Parents and Children in Covenant-obedience and bleſſing, at that great Day. This is the principal Deſire and Soul-travel of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The Lords unworthy Servants, who in reference to Infants do rejoyce in our Miniſtry: <hi>John Angier. John Hariſon. Nathaneel Rathband. William Meek.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>March</hi> 10. 1652.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:44967:4"/>
            <head>THE Authors Preface to the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theſe times the Lords Builders are compelled while <hi>they with one hand work in the work,</hi> with <hi>the other hand to hold the weapon:</hi> Some <hi>wiſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-builders have been valiant</hi> for the Doctrine and practiſe of Paedobaptiſm, whileſt others <hi>have bent their tongues like a Bow</hi> againſt it: Some of them I have <hi>ſeen,</hi> and made uſe of; ſome I have <hi>heard of,</hi> not <hi>ſeen;</hi> others (poſſibly) there are which I have neither <hi>ſeen</hi> nor <hi>heard of.</hi> However, I deſire that if any <hi>wiſdom</hi> or <hi>ſtrength</hi> be diſcerned in this <hi>Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> it may be eſteemed firſt <hi>Gods,</hi> then <hi>theirs;</hi> the <hi>weakneſs</hi> hereof is not <hi>theirs</hi> (much leſs <hi>Gods</hi> or the <hi>Cauſes</hi>) but <hi>mine</hi> own; yet I humbly hope this poor pains will be <hi>acceptable</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>chiefeſt Maſter-builder</hi> and <hi>Captain of his Hoaſt,</hi> and alſo (thou helping together with thy prayers) profitable to <hi>thee</hi> his <hi>ſervant</hi> and <hi>Soldier.</hi> Satan our grand Enemy would prevail (if he could) for ſuch a <hi>groſs renunciation</hi> of Baptiſm (received in Infancy) as Witches, Wizzards (his devoted Vaſſals) and open <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> do make: but having no hope at firſt to prevail ſo far, he endevors to bring-us by a <hi>pretence</hi> of <hi>purity</hi> to ſuch denyal and renunciation of Infant-Baptiſm as the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> do make, which hath been very advantagious to his Kingdom as well in <hi>Germany</hi> as in other places; the more ſad it is to ſee that ſome <hi>reputed,</hi> yea (poſſibly) <hi>real</hi> Saints, do in the ſimplicity of their hearts <hi>act</hi> and <hi>argue</hi> for him in <hi>this</hi> buſineſs, as <hi>Peter</hi> did in <hi>another,</hi> Mat. <hi>16.22, 23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The various turnings, <hi>crooked ways</hi> and windings of the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent</hi> in this Controverſie (as I could in ſo ſhort a time and piece) I have endevored to diſcover, and to make the <hi>paths of the Lord ſtraight</hi> and <hi>plain</hi> to his people. <hi>Repetitions</hi> (for brevity ſake) I have avoyded, even where they might have been ſomewhat uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, by reaſon of which ſome parts hereof taken by themſelves may
<pb facs="tcp:44967:5"/>ſeem more <hi>dark</hi> and <hi>defective</hi> then (I hope) they will be found if thou compare one place with another, and ſpare thy cenſure of <hi>any part</hi> till thou haſt read the <hi>whole.</hi> I have kept cloſe to the <hi>main matter,</hi> viz. <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> not omitting any Objection of the <hi>Catechiſt</hi> againſt it; but I have purpoſely ſlighted <hi>by-matters,</hi> leſt this Book ſhould be <hi>voluminous,</hi> or I ſeem to be <hi>contentious</hi> above what is meet. I have deſired to ſpeak <hi>rationally</hi> to the <hi>cauſe,</hi> and durſt not bring any <hi>railing accuſation</hi> against <hi>perſons.</hi> My <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> is this, the testimony of my <hi>conſcience</hi> that <hi>in ſimplicity and godly ſincerity</hi> I have managed this matter, not daring <hi>to talk de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully for God,</hi> or willingly to wrong any. The worſt I wiſh to my Antagonists in this cauſe, is, that both they and I may be ready to <hi>receive</hi> every revealed <hi>Truth of God</hi> both in the <hi>light</hi> and <hi>love</hi> of it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44967:6"/>
            <head>THE Catechiſt Catechized: OR, AN EXAMINATION OF AN <hi>Anabaptistical Catechiſm,</hi> Pretended to be Publiſhed for the Satisfaction and Information of the People of God in <hi>Lancaſhire, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>ANABAPT. CAT.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Who are fit Subjects for Baptiſm?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. <hi>Onely ſuch as beleeve,</hi> Acts 8.12.37. <hi>lſo</hi> Acts 16.34. <hi>alſo</hi> 18.8. Mat. 28.19. <hi>And ſuch as repent,</hi> Acts 2.38. <hi>and</hi> Mat. 3.6.</p>
               <p>NOne of theſe Texts ſeverally, nor all of them joyntly,<note place="margin">Exam. Chap. <hi>1. §. 1.</hi>
                  </note> do prove, That <hi>only ſuch as believe, and ſuch as repent, are fit Subjects for Baptiſm:</hi> nor do they ſo much as ſhew, That any ſon or daughter of Chriſtian Parents (ſuch as we baptize in Infancy) did believe, or repent, or make profeſſion of Faith and Repentance, before they were, or could be admitted to Baptiſm.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 16.34. doth not evince, that the Jaylors houſe or family rejoyced or believed, (as you ſeem to underſtand it;) for the Text
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:44967:7"/>(<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, being of the ſingular number) may thus be read, He <hi>believing, rejoyced,</hi> or <hi>expreſſed his joy (having believed) in all his houſe,</hi> by feaſting <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> in his houſe, whither he had brought them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 34. Or (if by <hi>houſe</hi> be meant his Family) he rejoyced in or amongſt his Family, becauſe of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made to him, <hi>v.</hi> 31. That if he did <hi>believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (as now he did) <hi>he ſhould be ſaved, and his houſe:</hi> And if any Infants of the Jaylor might be in the number of thoſe that ſhould be <hi>ſaved</hi> (as you will confeſs they might,) why might they not be alſo in the number of thoſe that were <hi>baptized?</hi> Beſides, this <hi>believing,</hi> of whomſoever it is ſpoken, is not in the Text ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed to have been before they were baptized; for it is ſaid, <hi>ver.</hi> 33. That <hi>he and all his were baptized ſtraightway,</hi> or <hi>immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;</hi> after which, <hi>he brought them into his houſe, ſet meat before them, believing in God.</hi> So this very Chapter, <hi>v.</hi> 14, 15. ſaith of <hi>Lydia,</hi> that <hi>Paul</hi> preached to her, and <hi>ſhe heard, and attended to thoſe things that were ſpoken of Paul;</hi> but none of theſe things are ſpoken of her houſe, yet they were baptized as well as ſhe. It it true, it is ſaid, that <hi>Paul preached</hi> to the Jaylor, and <hi>to all that were in his houſe,</hi> v. 32. and that <hi>Crispus believed in the Lord with all his houſe, Acts</hi> 18.8. Yet this (you know) doth not ſhew that there we none but actual Believers in the houſhold. <hi>Abraham Gen.</hi> 18.19. is ſaid <hi>to command his children and ſervants to keep Gods way;</hi> and ſure his houſe might be called a <hi>believing houſe:</hi> And now, we call <hi>godly families, praying families,</hi> though there be children in them not capable of underſtanding or obeying the Word, or of actual believing and praying. Now ſeeing the Jay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, <hi>Lydia,</hi> and their, and other houſholds, are ſaid to be baptized, (as <hi>Abraham</hi> and his houſe were circumciſed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.) and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing children are part of the houſhold, and often included (if not chiefly intended) under that name, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.36. <hi>&amp;</hi> 45.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 46.5. with <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.1. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.15. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 17.12, 13, with 15. and that there are ſo few families without little ones; Who dare affirm, and can prove, That there were none in theſe families? or that they were excluded from Baptiſm? ſeeing the Scripture doth not exclude them, (as elſewhere upon juſt cauſe it expreſly doth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.8.) Nor do we read of whole houſholds admitted to the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> as we do to <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> though your principles are as much for the <hi>one</hi> as for the <hi>other:</hi> So that ſome
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:44967:7"/>Texts, by you brought to overthrow <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> do afford at leaſt a very probable Argument for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.6. names <hi>confeſſing of ſin</hi> (which is oft too far from <hi>repentance,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">§. 2.</note>) probably to <hi>God,</hi> not to <hi>John;</hi> or if to <hi>John,</hi> not a <hi>particular</hi> confeſſion of each of them by himſelf (which Papiſts from hence urge,) for it was not poſſible for <hi>John</hi> to hear the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular confeſſions of ſo many, as for their multitude deſerved to be called, <hi>Jeruſalem, and all Judea, and all the region round about Jordan,</hi> in any convenient time: But whatſoever confeſſion it was, it ſeems it was not <hi>before</hi> their Baptiſm (as you would have it) but <hi>after;</hi> for it ſaith, they were baptized, not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>having confeſſed,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>confeſſing</hi> their ſins; and it is not ſaid, they were baptized becauſe they had repented, but rather on the contrary, that <hi>John's</hi> Baptiſm was a Baptiſm <hi>unto Repentance,</hi> v. 11. This, you know, is conſiſtent enough with Infant-Baptiſm. As for <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. it is probable, that <hi>repentance,</hi> to which (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <hi>their being pricked in their hearts,</hi> v. 37.) the Apoſtle exhorts, was in them only in <hi>fieri</hi> before their Baptiſm, for imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after this Exhortation they were baptized; and there could not be time to queſtion three thouſand in one day after Sermon (which, conſiſting of many main points, muſt needs be long, and <hi>three</hi> of the <hi>twelve</hi> hours of the day being ſpent before it begun, <hi>v.</hi> 15.) ſo as to make ſtrict enquiry into, and to take diſtinct notice of the repentance of each of them. Of <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.6. more hereafter.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe your Texts do ſhew, that the <hi>Samaritans,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">§. 3.</note> the <hi>Eunuch.</hi> the <hi>Jaylor,</hi> the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and others, which were then adult, and formerly either of the Jewiſh or Heatheniſh Religion, did believe, or profeſs faith and repentance, and were baptized; that is nothing to Paedobaptiſts, who never held, that a Jew or Heathen ſhould be baptized without profeſſion of faith. But grant further, That <hi>actual Believers,</hi> or <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> are indeed the <hi>primary</hi> and <hi>imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate</hi> ſubject of Baptiſm, and in their own right, and their children are but the <hi>ſecundary</hi> ſubject, and may not be baptized but by a capacity derived unto them; and at that time Chriſtian Churches were but <hi>in gathering,</hi> not <hi>gathered:</hi> The foundation was not to be layd in Infants, not in Infants only: And the ſacred ſtory, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating the manner of founding Churches, hath not ſo much occaſion to ſpeak of the Baptiſm of Infants, the <hi>ſecundary</hi> ſubject, as of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44967:8"/>actual believers, the <hi>primary.</hi> God created the firſt man and woman of a perfect age, though all their poſterity were born In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants: At firſt men of age were circumciſed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.24. with 14.14. and again after ſome intermiſſion of that Ordinance, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 5.4. And if any Nation had been Proſelyted, their men of age muſt firſt have been <hi>taught</hi> or <hi>diſcipled,</hi> and have made profeſſion of faith before they ſhould have been circumciſed, though in the ſetled condition of the Jewiſh Church Child-circumciſion was moſt in uſe. If Believers and Penitents ought to be baptized, will it thence follow, that none but they only are to be baptized? The rule is, <hi>A proprio primo modo ad proprium ſecundo modo non valet argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum:</hi> All Crows are black, therefore none but only Crows are black, is no good argument. If it were granted, that Infant-Baptiſm can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be proved by <hi>thoſe</hi> Texts, yet it will not follow, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be proved by any <hi>other</hi> Texts. Womens admiſſion to the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, though it cannot be proved by <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. <hi>Mark.</hi> 14. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. (<hi>Chriſt</hi> admitting only men,) may notwithſtanding be proved by other Scriptures. Your notion [That <hi>none are to be baptized but ſuch as they were, whoſe Baptiſm is mentioned</hi> Acts 8.12, 37. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.34. &amp;c.] is by ſome further improved, ſaying, All thoſe were ſuch Believers as had been in perſon Jews or Heathens, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch <hi>only</hi> are to be baptized; and <hi>thoſe that have Chriſtian Parents, and were educated in Chriſtianity from their childhood, are not (at leaſt not by virtue of any of thoſe Texts) to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized at all, neither in Infancy, nor when they make Profeſſion.</hi> As they in their caſe, ſo alſo you in your caſe are to blame, to inſert into your Anſwer the word <hi>[only]</hi> which you find in none of your Texts. Our Scripture-grounds for Infant-Baptiſm you ſhall hear anon, <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>ANABAPT. CAT.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>hat grounds have you againſt Infant-Baptiſm?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. <hi>Many; but chiefly Chriſts Commiſſion,</hi> Mat. 28.19. <hi>where the ſubjects of Baptiſm are thoſe that are made Diſciples, and this Commiſſion is to laſt to the Worlds end,</hi> v. 20. <hi>and reacheth to every creature that is to partake of Baptiſm, Mark.</hi> 16.15, 16.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>MAtth.</hi> 28.19. is not the <hi>firſt</hi> Commiſſion for <hi>baptizing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Examinat. Cap. <hi>2. §. 1.</hi>
                  </note> no more then for <hi>preaching. John Baptiſt,</hi> Mat. 3. and Chriſts
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44967:8"/>Diſciples, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1, 2. did baptize before this, and had commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for it, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.33. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.25, 26. which Chriſt confirmed by his being baptized by <hi>John, Mat.</hi> 3.13. Yea we have expreſs Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in Jewiſh Records of a Baptiſm,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>See Mr</hi> Selden, <hi>Dr</hi> Hammond, <hi>Dr</hi> Lightfoot, <hi>Mr</hi> Ainſworth, <hi>Mr</hi> Tombes.</note> which was a Rite of initi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation into the Jewiſh Church, a concomitant of Circumciſion, if not ancienter: So <hi>Jacob,</hi> admitting the preſerved <hi>Sechemites</hi> into communion (all of age being women,) bad them, be waſhed or <hi>baptized,</hi> or cleanſed by waſhing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.2. which is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why a Jewiſh <hi>Proſelyte</hi> is in <hi>Arrianus</hi> called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a <hi>baptized perſon:</hi> Hence the Jews did not queſtion <hi>John's</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm as a new and unuſual Rite, (they were already well acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it,) but his Authority to adminiſter it. <hi>Grotius</hi> on <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.6. conceives it was begun upon occaſion, and to preſerve the memory of the purging of the World by the Deluge, and that <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. ſignifies ſo much, calling Baptiſm the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>type</hi> and <hi>figure</hi> of it. And the Infants of the Jews were thus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, as well as the Proſelyte, for <hi>one Ordinance was for both, Numb.</hi> 15.15. And thus the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctors aſſert, (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Mr <hi>T.</hi> to the contrary pretends, that the Proſelytes only were baptized becauſe they were unclean,) That <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as well as others, <hi>entred into Covenant, Males by three things,</hi> viz. <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, Baptiſm, and Offering; Females only by the two laſt.</hi> Now, as <hi>Chriſt,</hi> aboliſhing the Paſſover, took the <hi>poſtcoenium,</hi> or common cuſtom uſed at the Paſſover, of the Maſter of the Family, his <hi>breaking a piece of bread, and diſtributing it, and a cup of wine,</hi> amongſt the company, to be materials of the <hi>Lords Supper;</hi> ſo he (aboliſhing Circumciſion and Offering) advanced this ancient uſual unqueſtionable concomitant of Circumciſion, and of initiation of Males, Females, Infants, or others, into the Church, to be a <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> the <hi>uſe</hi> whereof, and the <hi>perſons</hi> to whom it ſhould be adminiſtred, being then ordinarily and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly known, the Scripture did not need to record the commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or warrant given to <hi>John,</hi> or that the Jews had long before for their baptizing. It was enough, that there is not the leaſt hint in the Word, that Baptiſm, when advanced to be a divine Sacrament of the New Teſtament, ſhould not be applyed to Infants as it was before. Indeed when the Apoſtles Commiſſion was to be enlarged to <hi>all Nations,</hi> (this being a new thing, and rarely known or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved,) it was needful that it ſhould be ſet down <hi>in terminis,</hi> as it
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44967:9"/>here is: And yet this Goſpel was not written till about eight years after the Aſcenſion of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and other Goſpels were writ ſome years after this, the Jewiſh Church all this while be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guided by the Old Teſtament, and obſerving the Jewiſh lawful Rites and Cuſtoms, and this of baptizing doubtleſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others.</p>
               <p>You ſay,<note place="margin">§. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>The ſubjects of Baptiſm in the Text are ſuch as are made Diſciples, and therefore Christs commiſſion is againſt any other being baptized,</hi> particularly <hi>againſt Infant Baptiſm.</hi> But may not I as ſolidly argue, 1. The perſons here commiſſionated to baptize are ſuch as were <hi>made Apoſtles,</hi> had the gift of tongues, they were to go to <hi>all Nations,</hi> therefore none but A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles are to baptize? Or, 2. That none are to be baptized, but ſuch as by teaching or preaching the Goſpel to them are <hi>made Diſciples,</hi> though they be (as you know it is poſſible) converted by other means? Theſe Inferences, though weak, are as ſtrong as your: For ſuppoſe the Apoſtles being to <hi>Baptize the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> or Heathens (for to that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> relates notwithſtanding the gender here, aſwel as <hi>Act.</hi> 15.17. &amp; 28.28. &amp; 13.48. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14. 15.) were to preach to them, and thereby make them Diſciples doth that forbid that thoſe that are already Diſcipled ſhould have their children Baptized? None but <hi>Diſciples</hi> were to be circumciſed amongſt the Jews <hi>Act.</hi> 15.10. and yet children were circumciſed. If the Lord had given Commiſſion to <hi>Iſaiah</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah</hi> or any other to Proſelite <hi>all</hi> or <hi>ſome Nations,</hi> it had not been any whit incongruous and inconſiſtent with child circumciſion if the commiſſion had run in theſe very words, <hi>go teach all Nations,</hi> or <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that Nation,</hi> and <hi>Heathen people,</hi> and <hi>circumciſe them,</hi> and how then can the like ſpeech be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Infant Baptiſm, eſpecially ſeeing it was a thing ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly known that Infants were <hi>Baptized</hi> as well as <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed:</hi> ſee Sect. 1. And Infan's are as conſiderable a part of <hi>the</hi> other <hi>Nations,</hi> as they were of the Jews, in reference to whom other people were called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Heathen:</hi> and <hi>all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> ſome of all Nations or ſome of each ſort in the Nations, Infants amongſt others <hi>ſhould be bleſſed in Abraham, Gen.</hi> 18.18. He ſaith not, <hi>grown perſons,</hi> much leſs doth he ſay, <hi>grown perſons only;</hi> but, <hi>all Nations:</hi> nor is there any appearance of taking away by this Text any priviledg from Jewiſh Beleevers or their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44967:9"/>children, but only of enlarging their priviledges unto the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; The Apoſtles being commanded, that as they had preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Goſpel, and Sacramentally initiated the Jews only, ſo now they ſhould do the ſame to others alſo.</p>
               <p>If you inſiſt upon the order of the words, and argne thence,<note place="margin">§ 3.</note> that <hi>teaching</hi> (as the word is tranſlated) muſt go before <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing,</hi> you know there is no neceſſity, that what is ſet firſt in Scripture muſt alway be done firſt; ſometimes preaching is put before baptizing, and ſometimes baptizing before preaching, <hi>Mark</hi> 1.4. ſometimes repentance before faith, <hi>Mark</hi> 1.15. glory before virtue, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3. &amp;c. and here, as teaching is put <hi>before</hi> Baptiſm, ſo it is alſo put <hi>after</hi> Baptiſm, verſ. 20. To avoyd tautology in the words, <hi>Go teach-baptizing-teaching,</hi> ſome godly learned men conceive the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould be tranſlated <hi>make Diſciples,</hi> or <hi>diſciple</hi> all Nations, which was the end of their miſſion; <hi>baptizing</hi> and <hi>teaching them,</hi> were the means of diſcipling them; whether they be ſet down in exact order of time or no, is not material. You (it ſems) urge the word in this ſence, and ſay in effect, <hi>that Infants are not Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples.</hi> It is anſwered both, that the phraſe to <hi>diſciple,</hi> or <hi>make Diſciples,</hi> anſwers an Hebrew phraſe among the <hi>Rabbins</hi> (the New Teſtament frequently uſing their phraſes in their ſence) which ſignifies <hi>admiſſion to be taught,</hi> though they were <hi>not yet taught,</hi> and in common uſe. Children the firſt day they go to ſchool, before they know any letter, or have any actual willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to learn. are called Scholers (the ſame with Diſciples) of ſuch a Maſter: And he that is liſted in an Army is called a Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, though poſſibly he know little or nothing of the art military: And Infants are Diſciples in the ſence and language of Scripture, as <hi>Act.</hi> 15.10. <hi>Thoſe upon whoſe neck the yoke</hi> of circumciſion (for of that te ſpeaks, as appears by Verſ. 1.5, 24.) <hi>was put,</hi> were not <hi>only</hi> nor <hi>moſtly</hi> adult, but Infants; nor did the Synod deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine againſt the circumciſion of grown men <hi>only,</hi> but <hi>alſo</hi> of Infants: Children are evidently called <hi>Gods ſervants, Levit.</hi> 25.41, 42. and they are as well <hi>diſciples,</hi> as <hi>ſervants.</hi> If <hi>Adam</hi> had not fallen, his children ſhould have been diſciples and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God (and ſo was <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his minority) not withſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their infancy. Beſides, it appears by comparing <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.42. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.3, 4, 5. <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.47, 48. &amp; <hi>Mark</hi> 9.41. that the <hi>ſame perſons
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44967:10"/>which belong to Christ</hi> (from which priviledg Infants in general are not warrantably excluded) <hi>are</hi> alſo <hi>the Diſciples of Chriſt,</hi> and that Infants are quickly capable of knowing Mothers and Nurſes from others of being taught actions and geſtures by them, and ſenſible of other things is very evident; much more are they capable of being taught by Chriſt, whoſe Diſciples they are, according to that promiſe, a part of the new Covenant, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.34. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 54.13. (others being but Gods uſhers and pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.2.) their Souls being as capable of being taught by <hi>God a Spirit,</hi> and <hi>Father of ſpirits,</hi> in their <hi>minor,</hi> as in their <hi>riper</hi> years; and experience teacheth, that ſome (not to mention <hi>Jeremy</hi> and <hi>John Baptiſt</hi>) being ſanctified from their infancy (ſo far as can poſſibly be diſcerned by men) have choſen the good, and hated the evil; a thing which neither their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture nor the art of man could teach them. When Parents be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, God makes himſelf over to them and theirs to be their God, and to teach them, and they make themſelves and theirs over to him to be his people and diſciples, and ſo children are diſcipled when their parents are; and if they be <hi>diſcipled,</hi> then by your own argument <hi>they are fit ſubjects of Baptiſm by virtue of Chriſts Commiſſion.</hi> Thus that which you call your chief Argument againſt Poedobaptiſm appears for it, not againſt it: Chriſts Command of <hi>diſcipling all Nations,</hi> and <hi>baptizing them,</hi> doth not exclude a part, and great part too, of the Diſciples of the Nations: <hi>Et non reſtringendum ubi Scriptura non reſtringit;</hi> If the Scripture doth not limit it ſelf, we muſt not limit it: You could tell us of houſholds without children, but ſure you will not tell us of <hi>Nations</hi> without children.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>the laſting of this Commiſſion to the worlds end, and the reaching of it to every creature that is to partake of Baptiſm,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">§. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.15, 16. If you will maintain the very ſame Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. &amp; <hi>Mar.</hi> 16. to teach ſo far and to laſt ſo long, and to be inalterable in any thing, you ſhould clear up theſe three things.
<list>
                     <item>1. That ſome perſons are now commiſſionated from God (as the Apoſtles hereby were) <hi>to go into all the world,</hi> and <hi>to teach all Nations.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. That <hi>caſting of Dovils, ſpeaking with tongues, heating the ſick,</hi> &amp;c. mentioned <hi>Mark</hi> 16. are to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually in the Church.</item>
                     <item>3. That Infants are there intended under the name of <hi>every creature,</hi> and that of them God doth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44967:10"/>require actual believing, as of as great or greater neceſſity to <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> then to <hi>Baptiſm:</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
The words are not, <hi>He that believeth not, ſhall not be baptized,</hi> but <hi>ſhall be damned:</hi> And are you as confident that all Infants are <hi>damned,</hi> as you are that none of them ſhould be <hi>baptized?</hi> I wonder you dare urge this Text againſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm, which your own heart tells you is as much or more againſt their <hi>Salvation,</hi> then againſt their <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> For my part, I conceive Infants are not to be ſcrued up to that proportion which God requireth of adult perſons: <hi>The Lord will take vengeance on them that know not God, that obey not his Gospel,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Every tree that bringeth not forth good fruit is hewn down, &amp;c. Mat.</hi> 3.10. Muſt therefore Infants either <hi>know God, obey the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and bring forth fruit,</hi> or he damned? May we not feed and clothe Infants, becauſe the Word ſaith, <hi>He that will not labor, muſt not eat,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.10. Might not the Jews admit Infants into the viſible Church, becauſe the Pſalmiſt deſcribes the Citizen of <hi>Sion</hi> (you ſay, a Church-member) <hi>Walking uprightly, working righteouſneſs ſpeaking the truth in love, contemning vile per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons? &amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 15.1, 2, &amp;c. The application is eaſie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>ANABAPT. CAT.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What atker grounds have you againſt Infant-Baptiſm?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. <hi>Infants are not fit ſubjects for Baptiſm becauſe they do not believe, they have not reaſon to diſcern between good and evil,</hi> Deut. 1.39. <hi>Faith is an act of the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which cometh by hearing, as well as an act of the Will; and it is unlawful to baptize perſons without they believe,</hi> Acts 8.37. <hi>if thou believeſt, it is lawful,</hi> Act. 10.47. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.8.</p>
               <p>ALL the Textt you now produce have been anſwered before in the firſt Chapter;<note place="margin">Examinat. Cap. <hi>3. §. 1.</hi>
                  </note> ſave <hi>Acts</hi> 10.47. from which you may collect, That thoſe that had the <hi>gift of the Holy Ghoſt</hi> (as it is call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>v.</hi> 45.) and <hi>could ſpeak with tongues, v.</hi> 46. were to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized; but ſure you will not infer thence, That thoſe that have not the ſaid gifts are not to be baptized: If you do, you will deny all Baptiſm that is now adays, and turn <hi>Seeker.</hi> But as by your Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples you hold Confeſſion of Faith and Repentance ſufficient to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44967:11"/>Baptiſm, without thoſe gifts; ſo you ſhould ſhew, that the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid gift, and ſpeaking with tongues, was in ſtead of their believing and repenting; or elſe confeſs, that you impertinently alledg this Text.</p>
               <p>I muſt now ask you once for all,<note place="margin">§. 2.</note> what you mean by <hi>Believers?</hi> whether ſuch only as have a true juſtifying Faith; or all that make profeſſion of Faith, whether indeed and in truth they have a true juſtifying Faith or no? The firſt is requiſite in <hi>foro Dei, &amp; conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae, &amp; ex parte baptizati,</hi> that our Baptiſm may be acceptable to God, and comfortable to us, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. So the <hi>Eunuch</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring Baptiſm with the ſaving benefit thereof, and asking, not, <hi>What doth hinder thee from baptizing me?</hi> but, <hi>What doth hinder me</hi>—was anſwered, <hi>If thou believeſt with all thy heart, thou mayſt.</hi> But in <hi>ſoro Eccleſiae, &amp; ex parte baptizantis,</hi> the latter ſufficeth for admiſſion, your ſelf being judg: No Scripture-rule was tranſgreſſed when <hi>Judas, Simon Magus, Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phira</hi> were baptized. The <hi>Eunuch's</hi> profeſſion, That he <hi>believed Jeſus Chriſt to be the Son of God,</hi> ſufficed to preſent admiſſion of him to Baptiſm. And ſurely not the <hi>inward</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual</hi> qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but the outward and viſible eſtate of perſons to be baptized is to be looked at; and we ſhould deſcend to the <hi>loweſt</hi> (perſonal profeſſion of Faith and Repentance being the <hi>higheſt</hi>) degree of viſibility: Suppoſe a Miniſter had a ſpirit to diſcern the inward eſtate of men as certainly as <hi>Chriſt</hi> did of <hi>Judas,</hi> and poſſibly the Apoſtles did of ſome which they baptized; yet were he not to withhold from any, for want of inward grace, the priviledges which they have right and title to by virtue of their viſible eſtate. Saint <hi>Auguſtin</hi> and others think, <hi>Judas</hi> was admitted to the Lords Supper, though he but received <hi>panem Domini,</hi> not <hi>panem Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num:</hi> and Mr <hi>Cartwright</hi> alſo ſo judgeth, from that connection, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.19, 20, 21. Certainly he was admitted to the Paſſover by virtue of his viſible eſtate. <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> were regularly cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, though <hi>Abraham</hi> knew that the one, and <hi>Rebecca</hi> that the other, was not the Elect ſeed of the Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.19, 20. with 23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 25.23 <hi>Rom.</hi> 9 12. We can but <hi>charitably</hi> judg, not <hi>infallible</hi> know, who are Believers; and though Infants do not actually believe, yet by the judgment of charity (if that he our rule) we ought to judg, that Infants born of Chriſtian Parents are regenerate, and have faith habitual, or the principle or ſeed of it,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44967:11"/>ſo much as is abſolutely neceſſary to their participation of Chriſt, and Salvation by him, and that they dying in Infancy are ſaved: ſee <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. For though they cannot <hi>actually</hi> believe, or at leaſt not make a profeſſion of their Faith, yet they are not to be doom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Infidels,</hi> no more then they are to be judged <hi>irrational</hi> or <hi>dumb,</hi> becauſe they cannot actually reaſon or ſpeak; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they (unleſs you can reduce them to a third party, which will much ſtrengthen the Popiſh conceit of a third place for them when they dye, <hi>Limbus Infantum,</hi>) are to be counted <hi>Believers;</hi> and ſo methinks Chriſt accounteth of them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.6. with 4.</p>
               <p>Ever ſince God gathered a diſtinct number our of the World to be his Church, viſible Kingdom, City and Houſhold,<note place="margin">§. 3.</note> in oppoſition to the reſt of the World, which is the viſible Kingdom, City, or Houſhold of <hi>Satan,</hi> God would have the Infants of all who are taken into Covenant, to be accounted <hi>his,</hi> and to belong to his Church and Family, and not to the Devils. If <hi>Adam</hi> had kept the Covenant of Works, his Infant ſeed had been righteous; <hi>Adam</hi> breaking that Covenant, his Infant ſeed was guilty of that breach, and became ſinners againſt the Law, though they knew not what the Law, or ſin againſt it, was: <hi>Adam</hi> being within the Covenant of Grace, his Infant ſeed was ſo judged likewiſe: For by <hi>ſeed of the woman, Geneſ.</hi> 3.15. is meant Chriſt in his <hi>minority,</hi> as well as in his <hi>grown years,</hi> who dyed for Infants as well as others, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are infants to be excluded from the benefit of that Promiſe: The Infants of <hi>Noah, Abraham,</hi> and the <hi>Jews,</hi> were members of the ſame Church with their Parents: As Infants of <hi>Jews, Turks,</hi> and <hi>Pagans,</hi> though uncapable of thoſe Opinions or Practiſes, are eſteemed <hi>Jews, Turks, Pagans;</hi> ſo the Infants of Chriſtians (though, as the children of men, they are <hi>born in ſin, Pſal.</hi> 51.5. <hi>dead in it, Epheſ.</hi> 2.1, 3.) yet, as <hi>children of the Church,</hi> they are viſibly Chriſtians, not <hi>Inſidels, Jews, Turks,</hi> or <hi>Pagans.</hi> Though a Noble-man, a Free-man of a Corporation, a viſible Church-member, do beget children as men, not as a perſon of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, a Free-man, a Church-member; yet according to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Charters, the Honor of the one, the Freedom of the other, and Church-priviledges of the third, may deſcend on their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:44967:12"/>
               <head>ANABAPT. CAT.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What other Arguments have you to prove, That Infants have not Faith, and are not to be baptized?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. <hi>If they had Faith, they were preſently to be admitted to the Supper, and not excluded from communion therein, as many are, which are admitted to communion in Baptiſm, whereas the communion in both is one and the ſame, the ſame thing ſignified in both,</hi> viz. <hi>our fellowſhip with Chriſt in his Death and Reſurrection: So that all that are baptized into one body, are all made to drink into one Spirit,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.13. <hi>and the ſame preparations of Faith and Repentance are required for both; and he that is caſt out of the one, is caſt one of the other, ſeeing by excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication he is like an Heathen or Publican.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>IT is the Judgment both of Mr <hi>Rutherford,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exam. Chap.</hi> 4. §. 1.</note> and Mr <hi>Hooker,</hi> and others of <hi>New-England, That Infants of viſible Churches, born of wicked Parents, members of the ſame Churches, ought to be baptized:</hi> The reaſon may be, We (when a Child is preſented to Baptiſm) are to take notice of the Parents Church-memberſhip, not of his ſcandalouſneſs: If the Church do not caſt out the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, why ſhould the Miniſter caſt out the Child? Parents, where ſuſpended, loſe only their preſent fruition, not their fundamental right to memberſhip: It is right to memberſhip, not the preſent fruition of it, nor their worthineſs of that right, doth (as they conceive) transfer that priviledg to Infants. Mr <hi>Cotton</hi> in his <hi>Way,</hi> p. 115. conceives it is conſiderable, <hi>if the Grandfather or Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother, making profeſſion, be ſtill living, and willing to undertake for the Child;</hi> yea, that in ſome caſes a <hi>Heathens child may be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in right of its houſhold-governor, Gen.</hi> 17. Yet it is very far from their Opinions, That theſe children, or the immediate Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of them ſhould be admitted to the Supper.</p>
               <p>Amongſt the Jews Infants were circumciſed,<note place="margin">§. 2.</note> yet were they not preſently admitted to the Paſſover; they could not <hi>come up</hi> (nor do we read they were <hi>carryed</hi>) from the remote parts of <hi>Judea</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where only the Lamb was eaten, nor could they eat it ſtanding <hi>with ſtaves in their hands,</hi> and <hi>with ſowr herbs,</hi> as was required, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. nor <hi>keep it to the Lord,</hi> verſ. 46. with
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:44967:12"/>ſpiritual reſpects to Gods glory, to Gods ends and rules, and to have their <hi>hearts prepared,</hi> as well as to be ceremonially clean, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18.19. and the ſame males were as well to be at the feaſt of tabernacles (as at the Paſſover) and to carry boughs (which was no Infants work) to make booths or tabernacles to dwell in, <hi>Deut.</hi> 16.16, 17. with <hi>Levit.</hi> 23.34, 35 38, 39 40. The children, yea thoſe that could ſpeak and ask queſtions, did not partake of the Paſſover, as is implyed in that they did not ſay, what mean <hi>we,</hi> but what mean <hi>you</hi> by this ſervice? <hi>It was not allowable to count</hi> them for the eating of the Paſſover <hi>that could not eat of it,</hi> viz. <hi>Infants, ſick perſons, uncircumciſed and unclean;</hi> ſee <hi>Ainſw.</hi> in <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.4. The uncleanneſs of a Proſelyte was no bar to Circumciſion, but to the Paſſover it was, <hi>Numb.</hi> 9.6, 10. An adult Proſelyte might in ſome caſe be circumciſed and baptized, and not preſently admitted to the Paſſover: <hi>Ainſw.</hi> in <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.44.</p>
               <p>The Rite of Baptiſm is after the common cuſtom of <hi>waſhing new born Infants</hi> from the pollutions of the womb,<note place="margin">§. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. 5, 9. but the elements of <hi>bread and wine are the food of riper</hi> years. Baptiſm is a Sacrament of <hi>Initiation</hi> (as <hi>Bernard</hi> calls it,) the Supper is the <hi>higheſt</hi> Ordinance, Chriſtians (as ſuch) are capable of. It is one thing to be <hi>admitted a Scholar</hi> in a School, or to be <hi>matriculated</hi> into the Univerſity; another thing to be of <hi>ſuch a form, ſtanding,</hi> or <hi>degree:</hi> It is one thing to be a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, a tenant, or free of a Corporation (which children may be,) another to do homage, ſuit and ſervice. Our Regeneration or birth in Chriſt (whereof Baptiſm is the laver) Infants are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of; but not of that growth and augmentation ſignified in the Supper. To be baptized, is to be <hi>paſſive</hi> (as in the firſt act of Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration we are meerly paſſive) the action is wholly the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizers, <hi>I baptize thee, &amp;c.</hi> but to eat and drink in remembrance of <hi>Chriſts</hi> death, and to diſcern the Lords body, is to be <hi>active,</hi> and requires exerciſes of reaſon and grace. And as <hi>Chriſt</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>did not adminiſter Baptiſm,</hi> but his <hi>Diſciples, Joh.</hi> 4.1, 2. <hi>Paul</hi> faith, <hi>God ſent him not to baptize;</hi> the Apoſtles did not ſo uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally baptize, as ordinary Miniſters, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.14, 15, 17. but Chriſt did adminiſter the Lords Supper, as alſo the chief Miniſter pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent did uſually afterward: So multitudes were <hi>baptized</hi> by <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> and the Diſciples of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which were not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44967:13"/>admitted to the Supper when <hi>Chriſt</hi> inſtituted it. The Apoſtles were to <hi>teach all Nations, baptizing them;</hi> but the <hi>communicating of all Nations</hi> is not expreſſed; of the <hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> and ſeveral houſholds baptized, we read; of their preſent admiſſion to the Supper, we read not: So that though the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in both the Sacraments be one, and the preparations for them both in adult perſons be the ſame for ſubſtance, yet becauſe of their different diſpenſations and degrees, Infants may be admitted to the one, and not to the other. Yet I freely and confidently aſſert, <hi>that to admit children to the Supper, is far more excuſable then to deny them Baptiſm;</hi> for they have <hi>jus ad rem,</hi> a right to it (as a young heir hath to his lands,) as Saints decayed in mind and body have a right to hear the Word; and the communicating of Infants is of more antiquity and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit in the Church, then denying of their Baptiſm; though I hold it not fit that Infants ſhould communicate, becauſe they have not <hi>jus in re,</hi> they have not aptitude and fitneſs for it: a child is not fit to manage his own eſtate; nor is it rational to preach the Goſpel to an holy man (what right ſoever he may have to it) when he is deſtitute of capacity to hear or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it: and hence it is, that the Church having ſome while admitted Infants to the Lords Supper, did upon ſecond conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations diſcern her miſtake, and lay it aſide, but yet ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued that other of baptizing Infants, ſeeing no cauſe to leave it off, but rather more ſtrictly to obſerve it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>ANABAPT. CAT.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>But what if an Infant, or any other in their childhood, ſhould dye unbaptized, are they not damned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. <hi>We know nothing out of the Scripture of their Salvation or Damnation, and therefore we muſt not be too inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive; yet may ſuch Infants ſo dying be ſaved, through the preſentment of the ſatisfaction of Chriſt to the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God for original ſin, which Satisfaction, though it be applyed through beleeving in thoſe that can beleeve, yet it may be applyed without in thoſe that cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, elſe how could any Infants be ſaved?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>IF you know nothing of their Salvation,<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth; <hi>Mark</hi> 10.14. <hi>Of ſuch,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is the Kingdom of Heaven:</hi> He
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:44967:13"/>means, not only thoſe that are meek, humble, harmleſs, <hi>like little children,</hi> (for he would not have <hi>blamed thoſe that would have kept little children from him,</hi> nor have <hi>bleſſed them</hi> when they came, if they were only meer emblems of ſuch as are bleſſed, as a Lamb or a Dove may be,) but <hi>little children themſelves. David</hi> judged, that his child, though adulterouſly begotten, and whom God took away in his wrath, was ſaved, elſe he would not have eaten, and drunk, and rejoyced that he ſhould go to it, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.20. If any affirm, <hi>That all Infants of Chriſtians dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Infancy are certainly ſaved,</hi> I know no Scripture againſt it; and if there be no place punctually proving it, we are bound to encline to the more charitable opinion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.1. eſpecially when we ſpeak of this or that particular Infant. You ſay, they may be ſaved without Baptiſm; true, there is a poſſibility of it: ſo if Infants of the Jews had not been circumciſed the eight day, and had dyed uncircumciſed, they might alſo have been ſaved, (their parents or governors being guilty of the contempt or neglect of the Ordinance, not they; and why ſhould their Salvation or Damnation depend upon others doing or not doing their duty?) That phraſe of <hi>cutting off, Gen.</hi> 17.14. either concerns grown men only, or threatens only <hi>excommunication</hi> or <hi>death,</hi> not eternal damnation. God had mercy on the penitent thief; yet it is preſumption in us to defer repentance till death, or to neglect Baptiſm. God can bring a child into the world without a midwife; ſhall we therefore neglect the means? Parents when their children are baptized before they dye, may not only be comforted in the performance of their duty, but alſo have more grounded hopes of their childrens Salvation: Your Antipoedobaptiſtical Doctrines do take away all or moſt of the grounds of hope which Chriſtian parents have of the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their dying Infants.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>ANABAPT. CAT.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whether do you think it were better for perſons to have Baptiſm deferred till they be able to make a profeſſion of faith.</hi> A. <hi>Yes, it would be far better, for hereby the Churches would have right matter.</hi> (i.e.) <hi>Saints in profeſſion, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons would be careful to get knowledg and holineſs, whereas now they are careleſs of hoth: Infant-haptiſm brings many miſchiefs, beſides that it fills the Church with rotten members, confounds the Church and the world together, and is a groundwork for more tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and doth ſo darken the Doctrine of Baptiſm, that we cannot know the true meaning of it when we read it in Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:44967:14"/>
               <p>THe many <hi>miſchiefs of Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> and <hi>the benefis of ſuch delaying</hi> of it,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Examinat. Cap.</hi> 6. § 1.</note> were unknown to the Apoſtolique Primitive Church, elſe ſure they would have left us ſome Precept or Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of their delaying the Baptiſm of the children of Chriſtian parents. The Jewiſh Church had Child Circumciſion and Child Baptiſm too as Rites of Initiation; had it been better they had been deferred? was not the Jewiſh Church to be freed from miſchiefs (as you call them) as well as the Chriſtian Church? If Childrens admiſſion did not bring ſuch miſchiefs upon the Jewiſh, how comes it to be ſo miſchievous to the Chriſtian Church? We have a Command for Child-baptiſm, (not indeed ſuch a direct expreſs Command as they had for Circumciſion,) but a virtual, implicite and conſequential Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, as you ſhall hear anon, Chap. 10. and this is abundantly ſufficient to clear it from being a cauſe of it ſelf of any miſchief at all.</p>
               <p>You hold and pretend to prove,<note place="margin">§ 2.</note> that <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> and the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples of <hi>Chriſt</hi> did not baptize Infants; but were no rotten members baptized, when <hi>Jeruſalem, all Iudea, and all the rigion round about Iordan, came, and were baptized? Mat.</hi> 3. <hi>Mark</hi> 1. yea that <hi>people</hi> or <hi>multitude</hi> whom, or ſome of whom, he called <hi>Generation of Vipers, Luk.</hi> 3.7. with 21. Mr <hi>Cobbet,</hi> a <hi>New-England</hi> Divine, ſaith, <hi>Iohn Baptiſt did and might lawfully bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize thoſe multitudes, albeit in the general he knew that many, yea moſt of them, would prove falſe and frothy.</hi> Mr <hi>Nyes,</hi> another of them, ſaith, <hi>The Apoſtles for the baptizing of three thouſand ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected no teſtimonies, nor a day (much leſs a month or years) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, nor could they in ſo ſhort time make any inquiſitions, or hear any perſwaſive relations.</hi> When all the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> very lately <hi>bewitched</hi> by <hi>Simon Magus, Act.</hi> 8.9, 10. were baptized,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:44967:14"/>
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. was there then no rotten members? Suppoſe all <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Middleſex</hi> and all the region round about <hi>Thames</hi> or <hi>Trent,</hi> ſhould be Jews or Heathens (and ſurely you account them now much better) and ſhould preſently upon hearing of a Sermon make ſome profeſſion of faith, or confeſſion of ſins, and be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, would you judg all theſe right matter, Saints, and that there is no rotten member amongſt them? What became of thoſe multitudes and Myriads of baptized ones when Chriſt ſuffered, or afterwards if they were not rotten members? Were not <hi>Judas, Ananias, Saphira, Himeneus, Philetus,</hi> and many others, rotten members? Were there not amongſt the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> (though called <hi>Saints, a parte meliore;</hi> as we call a Whe it-field a Corn-field, though we ſee many tares and thiſtles in it) known carnal Schiſmatiques Fornicaters, Idolaters, ſome that ſacrificed to Devils, drunken Communicants, Heretiques denying the Reſurrection, Deſpiſers of <hi>Paul,</hi> Admirers of the falſe Teachers, Men (as <hi>Paul</hi> feared) that <hi>had not repented of the uncleanneſs, fornication and laſciviouſneſs they had committed,</hi> amongſt whom <hi>were debates, envyings, wraths, ſtrifes, back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitings, whiſperings, ſwelling tumults, &amp;c.</hi> were none of theſe rotten members? It is the work of the Miniſtry to convince rotten members of their rottenneſs, and by the bleſſing of God to convert them, and make them ſound, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.19. And if ſo be they remain incurable, and after much means, pains and patiences are not reclaimed, the Church may cut them off. Though the <hi>draw-net doth take in both good and bad,</hi> yet <hi>the bad</hi> afterward <hi>may be caſt away, Matth.</hi> 13.47.48.</p>
               <p>Are there not alſo amongſt the Anabaptiſts (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their rejection of Infant-Baptiſm) many rotten members,<note place="margin">§. 3.</note> Heretiques, Blaſphemers, ſuch as deny the Trinity, the Divinity or Humanity of Jeſus Chriſt, the Immortality of the Soul, the Morality of the Sabbath, Authority of the Scriptures, the guilt of original ſin, the neceſſity, yea very being of the Miniſtry, Officers and Ordinances; Aſſertors of the whole Body of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minianiſm, of immediate Revelations and Enthuſiaſms, of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinomianiſm, of Poligamy, perfection of grace? Who more then the Anabaptiſts (I had almoſt ſaid, who but they) have been given up by God to thoſe ſtrong and ſtrange deluſions,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:44967:15"/>to thoſe damnable Opinions and abominable Practices mentioned in the late Act? Where is there a more wicked and wretched Sect then the <hi>Ranters?</hi> But (poſſibly) you that publiſhed this Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm may be of the ſtricteſt Sect of your Religion, (as the worſt of theſe at their firſt ſeparating from us ſeemed alſo to be,) and do abhor to have communion not only with theſe, but with Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, Adulterers, Swearers, &amp;c. To you I ſay, if there be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you Drunkards, Adulterers, Swearers, &amp;c. (Satan himſelf is none of theſe,) but are there not ſeditious, ſchi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>matical perſons, that ſay, all <hi>the Church is holy?</hi> ſacrilegious perſons, that <hi>devour that which is holy,</hi> or dedicated to the ſervice of God and his Church, not by themſelves (which was <hi>Ananias</hi> his ſin) but by others? Are there not Murderers, Railers, falſe Accuſers, Lyars, proud, boaſters, covetous, traytors, heady, high minded, lovers of themſelves, deſpiſers of good men, having a form of godlineſs? &amp;c. Such an one is Satan. As for the rotten members in Paedobaptiſts Congregations, they are or ſhould be duly proceeded againſt, and much good is done that way in many Congregations where Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is ſet up, and people help forward the work, (humane infirmities both in Rulers and ruled ever have been, and will be:) And more good had been done, had not the ſeparation of ſome from us, the exemption by the Civil Powers from Church-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of whoſoever will not freely own it, the unjuſt clamors of <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> Rigidneſs and Tyranny, together with the Tumults and Troubles of the Times, hindred it.</p>
               <p>As for Infant-Baptiſm,<note place="margin">§. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>it is a conſecrating of children to God, and formally initiates them into the Church, which is a great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit,</hi> (as caſting out, or excommunicating out of the Church, is a great cenſure,) <hi>it is an outward diſtinctive ſign of Chriſtians chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren from Pagans, ſignifies their original ſin, and neceſſity of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, even before the commiſſion of actual ſin, and the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Infants, as well as grown men, by Chriſt: It makes In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants partakers of the Ordinances, at leaſt of the Prayers of the Church, as members thereof; it pre-engageth them to a Chriſtian Courſe, when they have the leaſt prejudice and obſtruction againſt it; and as ſoon as they are capable to receive the nurture and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of the Lord, to frequent Ordinances, to own Jeſus Chriſt by external profeſſion; it binds Parents to be more careful and conſcientious of their Religions Education, it comforts their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:44967:15"/>hearts</hi> (godly Parents may ſpeak this experimentally) <hi>to ſee their Children thus ſealed, in aſſurance that God is their God, and the God of their ſeed:</hi> Yea God doth ſometimes, yea always (as we ought to judg, till the contrary appear) baptize them <hi>inwardly,</hi> or in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſe grace, or the ſeed of it, into the Soul of the baptized Infant: Theſe, and the like were counted great benefits in the time of the Law; and are they, or can they be miſchiefs in the time of the Goſpel? You aſſert indeed, That <hi>delaying of Baptiſm would make men careful to get knowledg and holineſs, whereas now they</hi> (viz. they that do not delay Baptiſm) <hi>are careleſs of both:</hi> But may they not be as conſcientiouſly taught, and as careful and apt to learn in Chriſts School in his viſible Kingdom, as out of it? baptized, as unbaptized? Are not many grown perſons as forgetful and careleſs of the Promiſes they make on their ſick beds, and other occaſions, as of thoſe which were made in Infancy? Are <hi>Anabaptists</hi> the only men that are careful to get knowledg and holineſs? Are not multitudes of perſons, which were baptized in their Infancy, as careful to get knowledg and holineſs, and as good Proficients there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as any others? Is it better, not to put children into a leaſe or grant of a priviledg, leſt they ſhould be ſecure and careleſs to pay rent and do homage, then to put them in? May not deferring of Baptiſm ſo long, make them deſpiſe it when they come to age? Satan may more eaſily keep children, when grown up, from receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtianity, then work them to renounce it; though <hi>he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times prevails with Witches and Wizzards to renounce their Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> (received in Infancy) that they may be his vaſſals, and more aſſured to him. Keeping the children of Chriſtians out of the Church, is a ſtrange way (ſure it is none of Gods ways, nor is it likely to prevail to make them in love with Chriſtianity. If any good can be done by ſuch <hi>mediums,</hi> the warrantable deferring of the Lords Supper alone may do it, as well as the unwarrantable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laying of Baptiſm. As for <hi>darkening the Doctrine of Baptiſm,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience teacheth us, that the Doctrine thereof was clear enough in Scripture, and competently underſtood, as well as the Doctrine of the Lords Supper, before ſuch oppoſition hath been made to Infant-Baptiſm: If it be now darkened, the darkneſs is not from Infant-Baptiſm, but from your oppoſite Opinion and Practice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:44967:16"/>
               <head>ANABAPT. CAT.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>But may not Infants be baptized, if they be Abrahams ſeed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. <hi>Yes; But we Gentiles are only Abrahams ſeed by believing,</hi> Gal. 3.7. <hi>ſo</hi> Rom. 4.16. Gal. 3.29. <hi>They that would make the children of Believers to be the ſeed of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, are miſtaken; for the Scripture ſpeaketh but of three ſeeds of Abraham,</hi> viz. <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 3.16.2. <hi>The carnal ſeed:</hi> 3. <hi>The Believer, Jew or Gentile,</hi> Gal. 3.28. <hi>And they add a fourth ſeed of Abraham,</hi> viz. <hi>the ſeed or children of Believers amongst the Gentiles, about which the Scripture is ſilent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>EIther you do not ſufficiently <hi>enumerate,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exam. Chap. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> or <hi>not rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand your enumeration</hi> of the Scripture-kinds of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> ſeed, or both. For, 1. <hi>Chriſt perſonal</hi> is not the whole of <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, <hi>to</hi> whom (though he be the whole <hi>in</hi> whom, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20.) the Promiſes were made; but <hi>Chriſt myſtical,</hi> the whole Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12, 13. all which, <hi>whether Jews or Gentiles, bond or free,</hi> (I may add, <hi>young or old</hi>) are but <hi>one in their Head Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 3.28. <hi>All that are Christs are Abrahams ſeed,</hi> verſ. 29. and Infants are his, as well as grown perſons; for he became an <hi>Infant,</hi> ſuffered much in his very <hi>Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> was the Head of the Church while an <hi>Infant</hi> (and therefore might well have <hi>Infant-members,</hi>) dyed for <hi>Infants</hi> as well as for grown men, bad his Diſciples to ſuffer little children to come to him, (if not that he might baptize them, (for he <hi>baptized none at all,</hi> Infants or others, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1, 2.) yet that he might <hi>bleſs them,</hi>) and ſaid, that <hi>of ſuch is the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> 2. As for the carnal ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> their <hi>fleſhly relation</hi> was not ſufficient to entitle them to Church-priviledges, except they had a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation alſo, <hi>Rom</hi> 9 6, 8. Open Apoſtates, and Revolters, though the carnal ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> were not counted of the Church, but as <hi>ſtrangers,</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> calls them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 54.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 59.5. That Text, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.48. <hi>prohibiting ſtrangers, did by the rule of proportion prohibit from the Paſſover all ſuch Jews as did forſake the Faith:</hi> The <hi>Caldee Paraphraſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>No ſon of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, that is an Apostate, or fallen from the Faith, ſhall eat of it.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:44967:16"/>Cain</hi> and his poſterity were rejected, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.15, 16. <hi>cum Gen.</hi> 6.1, 2. So <hi>Iſhmael</hi> caſt out, and the <hi>Iſhmaelites, Gal.</hi> 4 30. <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.10, 14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83.6. which laſt place mentions the <hi>Edomites</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, which were the poſterity of <hi>Abraham;</hi> yea, all the twelve Tribes, which were the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> were caſt off at the laſt: and yet their being begotten after the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh, and being circumciſed in the fleſh, was an help, not an hindrance, to their being begotten of the Promiſe, or to Circumciſion in the Spirit. <hi>Jacob</hi> was of <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Rebecca</hi> after the fleſh, and yet alſo the heir of Promiſe: And as then ſome <hi>were born</hi> only <hi>after the fleſh,</hi> as <hi>Iſhmael, Eſau;</hi> and <hi>ſome were</hi> alſo <hi>born after the ſpirit,</hi> as <hi>Iſaac, Jacob:</hi> So the Apoſtle (looking not only to the <hi>Parallel,</hi> but to the <hi>Hiſtory</hi>) ſaith, <hi>So it is now;</hi> ſome, even in the time of the Goſpel, are born of Chriſtian Parents only <hi>after the fleſh,</hi> and ſome alſo <hi>after the ſpirit,</hi> and theſe do perſecute one another, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29. This difference may diſcover it ſelf in riper years, but in Infancy it is as undiſcoverable now as then. 3. It was not neceſſary that they ſhould be the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> that were in Covenant-relation, and initiated into the Church; for <hi>Abraham</hi> was (as to this) not only the <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Jews,</hi> but of <hi>many Nations,</hi> and upon this account his name was changed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.4.5. Proſelytes being <hi>Gentiles</hi> as well as we, and not of his <hi>carnal ſeed,</hi> nor (many) ſo much as <hi>of his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> yet they were the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> by <hi>believing,</hi> as wel as we are now; and they were not only initiated into the Church, but thoſe of them that were of <hi>Abrahams</hi> family were the foundationals, and firſt members of the Church, as conſtituted in <hi>Abrahams</hi> family; his 318 <hi>trained ſervants,</hi> beſides others, were not all (if any) of his carnal ſeed. 4. As for the Infants of Believers, which you ſeparate from their Parents (of which ſee before <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. §. 3.) and make them a <hi>fourth ſeed,</hi> you know that Proſelytes became <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed only by believing, as (you ſay) we <hi>Gentiles</hi> now do, and yet their children were accounted <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed (though they be none of the <hi>three</hi> which you mention,) and as ſuch were initiated into the Church, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.12, 23. <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.48, 49. In the ſame ſence that <hi>Abraham</hi> was a <hi>father</hi> to a Proſelyte, or <hi>believing Gentile and his ſeed</hi> then, he is a <hi>father to a Chriſtian Gentile and his ſeed</hi> now, for his Paternity abides the ſame; nor can you ſhew a better warrant for his Paternity over the <hi>one,</hi> then over the other, nor have the <hi>Gentiles</hi> loſt any priviledg by the coming of Chriſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:44967:17"/>which they had before: The Scripture ſaith, <hi>The Brethren now are the children of the Promiſe, as Iſaac was, Gal.</hi> 4.28. Now <hi>Iſaac</hi> was the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and in the Promiſe as an Infant of believing Parents, before he was an actual Believer, and his Infants wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> within the Covenant, and accordingly initiated into the Church. <hi>Abraham</hi> might ſay, <hi>God is my God, and the God of my Infant ſeed,</hi> and ſo might the <hi>Gentile</hi> proſelyted ſay alſo; and why may not a Chriſtian, who is <hi>bleſſed with faith-ful Abraham, Gal.</hi> 3.9. ſay ſo too? eſpecially ſeeing <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Circumciſion,</hi> did not abrogate, but <hi>confirm the Promiſes made unto the fathers, and that the Gentiles might glorifie God for his Mercy, &amp;c. Rom.</hi> 15.8, 9. God, alluding to the outward Circumciſion of his people, and their ſeed, promiſeth to <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe their hearts, and the hearts of their ſeed, Deut.</hi> 30.6. and this promiſe is <hi>Gospel,</hi> and a <hi>parcel of the Covenant of Grace,</hi> as appears by <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6, 10, 11, 12. with <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.6, 7, 8. and this circumciſion of the heart is commended <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.28, 29. and is ſignified and ſealed in Baptiſm, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.11, 12. It is obſerved, that <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. ſpeaks not of <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed (which (you ſay) are actual Believers) abſtractedly taken, but of <hi>his ſeed in their generations,</hi> which words neceſſarily imply and include, as the <hi>Parents generating,</hi> ſo <hi>the Children generated.</hi> Laſtly, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> is not only called the father of particular Believers, but the <hi>father of Nations</hi> profeſſing the true faith, as well as of the <hi>Jewiſh Nation:</hi> Every Nation receiving the true Faith as they did, and in which there is a National Agreement in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, as was in the Nation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> is an <hi>holy Nation, a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar people to the Lord,</hi> even <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and may call <hi>Abraham</hi> father, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 19.21. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.5. When the <hi>Gentiles were graffed into that ſtock from which the Jews were broken off, and did partake of the root and fatneſs of the Olive tree, Rom.</hi> 11.17. and <hi>Abraham</hi> began to be the <hi>father of many Nations, Rom.</hi> 4.16, 17. Regenerate Infants are <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſeed by Mr. <hi>T.</hi> his confeſſion, and he profeſſeth that he would baptize them, if he could know them. I am ſure no one dare ſay of this or that particular Infant, that it is not regenerate; yea, we are bound to judg they are ſuch, till ſomething appear to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:44967:17"/>
               <head>ANABAPT. CAT.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>But are not the children of godly perſons viſibly in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. <hi>No, the Covenant of Grace is an inviſible thing, and we cannot know who are in it, nor have we grounds to judg perſons are in it, till we ſee ſome profeſſion of holy life of faith and repentance, which Infants cannot make.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>NOt to ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k of ſuch as are only <hi>intentionally</hi> in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, as <hi>children yet unborn</hi> may be,<note place="margin">Examinat. Cap. <hi>8. § 1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.15. Thoſe that are <hi>Actually</hi> in the Covenant of Grace, are of two ſorts: Some are <hi>externally</hi> in it, as <hi>Iſhmael, Judas, Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus,</hi> and ſo all ſuch as own God to be their God, and themſelves to be his people (as the Jewiſh Church did, and every true Chriſtian Church doth) though but <hi>externally</hi> are ſaid to be within the Covenant: Your ſelf ſay, that <hi>profeſſion of faith and repentance are grounds to judg ſome perſons to be in the Covenant of Grace.</hi> There is external <hi>being in Chriſt, Joh.</hi> 15.2. <hi>Vocation, Mat.</hi> 22.14. <hi>Sanctification, Heb.</hi> 10.29. and <hi>purging from ſin,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9. But ſome are alſo <hi>internally</hi> and ſavingly in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, as <hi>Iſaac, Jacob,</hi> while Infants, and when adult, alſo <hi>Zacheus, Lydia</hi> and <hi>her houſhold,</hi> the Jaylor and <hi>all his.</hi> This diſtinction is grounded upon <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4, 6, 7, 8. We may know who is in the Covenant of Grace <hi>externally;</hi> but the Covenant of Grace in the ſecond ſence is inviſible, and none could know who were in it in the time of the Jews (though Infants were then <hi>viſibly</hi> in it, and initiated as ſuch) or amongſt Chriſtians. If the <hi>inviſibleneſs</hi> of the Covenant of Grace, and <hi>our not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing who are in it,</hi> doth exclude Infants, it doth alſo exclude adult Profeſſors from admiſſion into the Church; for the ſigns of their being <hi>ſavingly</hi> in the Covenant of Grace, are but conjectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, hopeful, and probable, not certain and infallible: none can be ſure, that he that makes profeſſion at a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll age, which quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies him for Baptiſm, is not an Hypocrite at this minute, and will not be an Apoſtate the next; nor can we know that they are in the Covenant, for then we ſhould know they are elected, whereas this is a <hi>ſecret known only to God,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.19. And the little ones of the Church, though they make no
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:44967:18"/>perſonal profeſſion, as adult perſons do, yet are as viſibly within the Covenant of Grace (parents having as much authority and reaſon to covenant for their children now, as <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.10. with 30 6.) and as charitably to be accounted of, ſeeing of adult Chriſtians the <hi>weakeſt</hi> can hold forth no more then the <hi>leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree</hi> of abſolute probability, and the <hi>ſtrongeſt</hi> no more then the <hi>higheſt degree</hi> of probability.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">§ 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38, 39. <hi>The promiſe is to you and to your children:</hi> Concerning which obſerve, 1. That hereby is not meant <hi>Christ is exhibited</hi> (as ſome gloſs,) The promiſe <hi>Is,</hi> id eſt, <hi>fulfilled,</hi> Chriſt is come; for this they had heard before, <hi>verſ.</hi> 36. and knew to their trouble, and therefore <hi>were pricked in their hearts:</hi> and theſe words are not any where in Scripture ſo taken; nor is Baptiſm a ſeal barely to Chriſt being come in the fleſh, but to the benefits thereof covenanted and promiſed; not is it a promiſe of the gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, but <hi>the promiſe</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Goſpel promiſe of <hi>remiſſion of ſin, Heb.</hi> 8.10, 12. ſigned and ſealed in Baptiſm, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.19. which belongs to Gods people at all times, might heal <hi>their being pricked in their heart, verſ.</hi> 37. and is fitly uſed as a motive to perſwade them to <hi>repent and be baptized,</hi> and is a ſuitable anſwer to their queſtion, <hi>What ſhall we do to be ſaved?</hi> 2. He ſaith not, <hi>The promiſe is to you, and to as many as God ſhall call, whether of your children or ſtrangers;</hi> as he might have ſaid, if he would have levelled the children of Chriſtians and Pagans: but he ſaith, <hi>The promiſe is to you and to your children, and to as many;</hi> making their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren a diſtinct party, as from thoſe that then <hi>were,</hi> ſo from thoſe that <hi>after</hi> ſhould be called; the words holding out their right, are in the Indicative Mood, The promiſe <hi>is</hi> to you: the like is never ſaid to Pagans, or to any out of the Church. 3. Theſe words are the ſame in ſubſtance with the reaſon and ground of Circumciſion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.8, 10, 11. That Promiſe and Covenant was a Goſpel Covenant, <hi>In thy ſeed ſhal all the Nations of the Earth be bleſſed;</hi> and was an <hi>everlaſting Covenant, made four hundred thirty years before the Law,</hi> and to be fulfilled in a great part of it after the ceaſing of <hi>Moſes</hi> Paedagogy, and of Circumciſion, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.15, 16, 17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>16, 24. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.20. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6. and the ſaid everlaſting Covenant was not only with <hi>actual Beleevers,</hi> but with the lineal ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> even before they actually
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:44967:18"/>believed, till ſome open revolt did diſable them, and with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-ſeed of Proſelytes or <hi>Gentiles</hi> converted to the ſaith. 4. His motion, that every one of them ſhould be baptized, doth imply, they had <hi>right</hi> to Baptiſm, (for he doth not perſwade them to be Uſurpers of that, to which they had no right,) and he grounds his motion not only upon their bare <hi>perſonal intereſt</hi> in the Promiſe, but their <hi>childrens joynt intereſt</hi> with them (as in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. God doth for Circumciſion,) which latter could not rationally be urged as a motive to perſwade <hi>the Jews to be baptized,</hi> and to embrace Chriſtian Religion, if the joynt intereſt of their children with them were not (at leaſt) fully as great in the Chriſtian as in the Jewiſh Church. Now if a Jew had a child born <hi>before</hi> his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to Chriſtianity, that child was Sacramentally to be initiated; but if he had a child <hi>after,</hi> you ſay it was not, but was in the ſame condition with a <hi>Pagans</hi> child, <hi>viz.</hi> not to be admitted into the Church till it were called: And if ſo, then where is the benefit be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the children of Jews converted by virtue of their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity? If a Landlord ſhould move his Tenants to give up his <hi>old</hi> Leaſe or Grant (which hath certain immunities and priviledges to him and his children) and to take a <hi>new</hi> one, in which his children ſhould have no more priviledges then meer ſtrangers; could he rationally perſwade him to ſurrender the old Leaſe or Grant, and to take a new one, from the benefit that may accrue to the Tenant and his children by it? 5. Here ſeem to be three ranks and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of perſons: 1. The Jews themſelves, then preſent and adult: 2. Their children, the preſent iſſue, which already was, or ſhould be born of their bodies, what ever they were, younger or elder, Infants not excluded: 3. Thoſe that were <hi>afar off,</hi> not in <hi>eſtate</hi> (for the myſtery of the calling of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> was not fully cloſed with by <hi>Peter</hi> till <hi>Act.</hi> 10. nor could the Jews yet bear that ſaying,) but thoſe that were afar off in <hi>time:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (we with <hi>Piſcator</hi> may add <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) is a different phraſe from that uſed of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.13, 17. and fitly may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note the poſterity of the Jews in after ages. 6. Theſe Jews (it's likely) were <hi>pricked in their hearts,</hi> not only for their <hi>crucifying of Chriſt,</hi> but <hi>their curſing their children</hi> about two months ſince, <hi>Matt.</hi> 27.25. which curſe did include their very Infants then new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly born, and others that ſhould be born afterward; and therefore if <hi>Peter</hi> had not included Infants in this Promiſe, the plaiſter had
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:44967:19"/>not been large enough for their ſore. Laſtly, The Jews were apt long after this to ſcruple leſſer matters, <hi>Acts</hi> 21.20. and can it be thought that they ſhould not ſtartle and be diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have both Circumciſion and Baptiſm taken from their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants? nor enquire whether this ſecluſion of their Infants was not a fruit of their curſing of them? or how it could be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Old Teſtament (there being then no other written Word?) or by what warrant the Church-memberſhip and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-intereſt, which their children formerly had, was repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and taken from them? By all which, ſeriouſly conſidered, it will appear, that the children of Believers are included within the Promiſe, and to be baptized. Beſide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, if Infants be not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Covenant of Grace, then they are <hi>ſtrangers</hi> from it, and conſequently <hi>without God,</hi> and <hi>without hope,</hi> as <hi>Pagans</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are; and if they dye (though in Infancy,) their Parents may <hi>mourn over them as ſuch that have no hope,</hi> contrary to 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.13. yea, while they live, they may lament over their children, as ſuch whom they have begotten and brought forth to the Devil, and not to God, in reſpect of their viſible eſtate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>ANABAPT. CAT.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Circumciſion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. <hi>It was an Obligation to keep the whole Law,</hi> Gal. 5.3. Rom. 2.24. <hi>and ſhewed unto them, that it was their duty to circumciſe their hearts,</hi> Jer. 4.4.</p>
               <p>CIrcumciſion in it ſelf was but an Obligation to <hi>the Law as a rule of Righteouſneſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Examinat. Cap. <hi>9. §. 1.</hi>
                  </note> ſubſervient to the Covenant of Grace (as Baptiſm alſo is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3.) not to the Law in <hi>the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor</hi> of it, as it was a Covenant of Works; for <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> were not ſo obliged, they were in the Covenant of Grace as well as we, and Circumciſion was to <hi>Abraham</hi> (by your own confeſſion) <hi>a ſeal of the righteouſneſs of Faith. Chriſt</hi> did profit may hundreds and thouſands that were circumciſed in the time of the Law, he was the <hi>Lamb ſlain from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the World,</hi> and they were ſaved by Faith in him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1, 2, 3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. but when Chriſtians were circumciſed in the time of the Goſpel, out of a perſwaſion of its neceſſity, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:44967:19"/>their juſtification by it, then it did bind them to keep the whole Law, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> in that caſe <hi>did profit them nothing;</hi> and this is all can be inferred from your Texts, as to this matter. As Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion did ſhew it was their duty to circumciſe their hearts, ſo Baptiſm ſhews <hi>it is our duty to waſh our hearts, Jerem.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.8. (between heart circumciſion and heart-waſhing is no great difference, if any.) And as there was a precept for the circumciſion of the heart, ſo God promiſed his people, that he will <hi>circumciſe their hearts, and the hearts of their ſeed;</hi> of which before <hi>Chapt.</hi> 7. Though Circumciſion did ſhew forth (you ſay) a Duty on our part, as well as a Promiſe on Gods part, yet (you know) Infants were then circumciſed, though they had no actual knowledg of either. What you can gather hence (if any thing) againſt Infant-Baptiſm, I expect to know.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>ANABAPT. CAT.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Was not Circumciſion alſo a ſeal of the righteouſneſs of Faith?</hi> Rom. 4.11.</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Yes, to Abraham only; and if Abrahams believing chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren amongst the Gentiles ſhould be baptized as he was circumciſed, then is muſt not be till they have the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Faith as Abraham here had, at leaſt they muſt have it in profeſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Text ſaith, <hi>It was the ſeal of the righteouſneſs of Faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">§. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>which Abraham had, being yet uncircumciſed;</hi> but it ſaith not, that <hi>it was ſo to him only:</hi> The Apoſtle brings it as an argument to prove the way of <hi>our</hi> Juſtification to be by Faith alone, which were a meer inconſequence, if proper to him, and not belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to others. There was adult perſons Believers in <hi>Abrahams</hi> Family when Circumciſion was firſt inſtituted, and many be-lieving Proſelytes afterward, which had Faith while yet they were uncircumciſed, as <hi>Abraham</hi> had, of whom their Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion alſo was a ſeal of the righteouſneſs of the Faith they had before; yea, <hi>Moſes</hi> makes it to all <hi>a ſign of the Covenant, Gen.</hi> 17. which doubtleſs was the Covenant of Grace; or, to uſe <hi>Pauls</hi> dialect, <hi>the righteouſneſs that is by Faith, Rom.</hi> 3.22 30. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.3, 6, &amp;c. <hi>cum Deut.</hi> 30.6, 10, 11, 12. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Tenor of that Covenant, <hi>Believe in the Lord Jeſus
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:44967:20"/>Chriſt, and thou ſhalt be ſaved, Acts</hi> 16.31. Your paſſage, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying, that there are ſome <hi>believing children of Abraham</hi> which have not the righteouſneſs of Faith as <hi>Abraham</hi> here had, I do not underſtand, except you make <hi>actual believing</hi> and <hi>having the righteouſneſs of faith</hi> two things, not only <hi>diſtinct,</hi> but <hi>ſeparable:</hi> But whatſoever your meaning be, I cannot ſee here any ſhew of proof, that children muſt neceſſarily believe, or make profeſſion of faith, before they may be baptized, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did before he was circumciſed. <hi>Abraham</hi> could not be circumciſed in Infancy, nor before Circumciſion was inſtituted, no wonder therefore if he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved before; had Circumciſion been inſtituted in the days of his fathers, <hi>Abraham</hi> might have been circumciſed before he actually believed, as well as <hi>Iſaac</hi> his ſon was. <hi>Chriſt</hi> could not be baptized till <hi>John</hi> did baptize, which was about the thirtieth year of Chriſts age, nor did he receive the Euchariſt till the night before he ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; yet ſome that pretend to imitate him, can be baptized, and poſſibly preach too, at 15, 16, 20, 21, &amp;c. years of age, though Chriſt was neither baptized, nor did preach, till he was thirty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>ANABAPT. CAT.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whether doth Baptiſm ſucceed Circumciſion in the ſame Office?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. <hi>No: Circumciſion was to every Male (though reprobate) but Baptiſm only to the Believer,</hi> Matt. 28.19. <hi>There being a change of the viſible Church, and of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, this cannot ſucceed in the room thereof, nor hath any dependance thereon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your Argument againſt the ſucceſſion of Baptiſm to Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion is weak,<note place="margin">§. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>viz. Baptiſm is not like Circumciſion in ſome things,</hi> therefore <hi>it is not like in any thing,</hi> therefore it ſucceeds not in the ſame office: By this you may prove as well, That <hi>the Supper doth not ſucceed the Paſſover,</hi> nor <hi>the Lords-Day the</hi> Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh <hi>Sabbath.</hi> The office of Circumciſion was to <hi>ſhew original ſin, to teach neceſſity of Regeneration, of Mortification, of Salvation by Chriſt, the ſeed of</hi> Abraham; <hi>to ſign and ſeal the Covenant, or the Righteouſneſs that is by Faith, to diſtinguiſh Jews from others, to initiate ſolemnly and formally into the Church:</hi> And doth not Baptiſm alſo initiate into the Church? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. Yea,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:44967:20"/>doth it not (Circumciſion being now abrogated) perform the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Offices? Indeed it is not every way the <hi>ſame,</hi> for then it were not <hi>a ſucceſſor.</hi> Add hereunto, that the <hi>Covenant</hi> was the ground of <hi>Circumciſion, Geneſ.</hi> 17.7, 9, 10, 11. the <hi>equity</hi> whereof ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligeth to Baptiſm, as the <hi>equity</hi> of the fourth Commandment ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to our Lords-Day. As for the <hi>poſitive command,</hi> verſ. 12. it only determines <hi>the time and day,</hi> which circumſtance of day and time was not built upon the Covenant of Grace (as Circumciſion it ſelf was) and therefore is not perpetual; and without ſuch a poſitive determination of the time, Circumciſion ſhould and might have been adminiſtred to Infants: the Jews did circumciſe children bought with their mony the ſame day they bought them, though they bought them the ſame day they were born: See <hi>Ainſw.</hi> in <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 17.12. Oft-times Circumciſion was not adminiſtred the eighth day, but deferred; in which caſes the command of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing the eighth day was not obſerved; yet Circumciſion was, and according to right reaſon ought, to be adminiſtred to Infants by virtue of the naked inſtitution thereof, as we contend that Baptiſm ought now to be, both of them being (as was ſaid) ſeals of the Covenant. But you, in ſaying <hi>Circumciſion was to every Male, though reprobate,</hi> do imply, that <hi>it Was not to Females;</hi> true: but both Males and Females were then baptized, and ſo they were in the New Teſtament, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.11. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28, 29. which is a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient juſtification of our deſerting Circumciſion in that point: And the Infant-females (as well as the adult) were counted members of the Jewiſh Church; and though, by reaſon of their incapacity, or Gods reſpect to the modeſty of that Sex, they were not perſonally circumciſed, yet they were circumciſed in the Males: Hence the whole Church of the <hi>Jews,</hi> conſiſting of Females as well as Males, were called the <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> in oppoſition of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which were called <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion, Gal.</hi> 2.7, 8, 9. Again, It was not <hi>adminiſtred to reprobates</hi> as ſuch, not to every Male, but to the <hi>Males of the Church</hi> externally in Covenant, ſome whereof poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly were Reprobates: So <hi>Simon Magus, Judas, Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphirah</hi> were baptized, and yet it is (at leaſt) likely that they were Reprobates. Circumciſion did belong to the Believer as well as Baptiſm doth; thoſe that were ſtrangers to the Jewiſh Church could not be admitted, but they muſt be <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> not <hi>of the gate</hi> only, but of <hi>righteouſneſs;</hi> they <hi>muſt diſclaim Paganiſm,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:44967:21"/>and profeſs the Jewiſh Religion:</hi> A ſtranger continuing in his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, was not circumciſed, not did partake in the Paſſover, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.48. And by proportion that Text prohibiteth all ſuch Jews as ſhould forſake the faith: See before <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. As for the change of the Church and Ordinances notwithſtanding it, the Lords-Day may ſucceed the Jewiſh Sabbath, and thoſe ſame perſons which were bound to keep the Jewiſh Sabbath, are tied to obſerve the Lords Day, <hi>viz. ſervants and children,</hi> as well as <hi>Parents and Maſters,</hi> though the perſons be not ſo diſtinctly ſet down in the New Teſtament as in the Old. <hi>Paul</hi> did uſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments from Analogy, from the <hi>purging out of the old leaven at the Paſſover</hi> to the <hi>caſting out of the inceſtuous from the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. from the <hi>maintenance of the Prieſts</hi> to the <hi>main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Ministers,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13. To argue <hi>à genere ad ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em affirmativè,</hi> is not good reaſoning; The Church was changed, therefore it was changed in this particular: The Church might be changed, and yet not in this; the Sacrament may be changed, and not the ſubject: what belonged to the Jewiſh <hi>Church</hi> as a <hi>Church,</hi> belongs to the Chriſtian Church alſo; that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to it as <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> was altered, as High-Prieſt, Temple, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, Ceremonies, &amp;c. Infants Church-memberſhip did not belong to the Church as <hi>Iewiſh,</hi> not was it a Ceremony or Type; if you think it was, ſhew what it was a <hi>type</hi> of, and what was the <hi>antitype</hi> that hath ſucceeded it, and prove it ſo you can. There was a Church, before there was an High-Prieſt, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, &amp;c. in the Families of <hi>Adam, Noah</hi> and <hi>Sem,</hi> which was alive in the time of <hi>Iſaac: Melchizedek</hi> ſurely had ſubjects and people, which were the Church (as well as he was a King and a Prieſt) of the moſt high God; This Church might continue long, &amp; not be united to the Church in <hi>Abrahams</hi> family for ought we know: whatſoever the extent of the Church was, Domeſtical, Congregational, or National, Infants are reckoned of the ſame Church with their Parents: the Church <hi>before</hi> Chriſt, and <hi>after</hi> Chriſt, is the ſame Church; as an Heir, <hi>While in nonage,</hi> and <hi>when adult,</hi> is the ſame perſon. The Jews that believed were never unchurched; the Tree was not broken down, but <hi>ſome branches broken off:</hi> ſome additionals to the Church ceaſed, the Church it ſelf ceaſed not; the <hi>partition Wall Was broken down,</hi> and <hi>Iews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> made <hi>one</hi> Church, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.6. And when
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:44967:21"/>the wall was down, were their Infants turned out of the Church at one door, as the Gentiles came in at another? was the Church ſo changed, that it loſt ſo many materials? and was the Covenant of Grace changed too? did it loſe ſo many out of it? Viſible Profeſſors and their Infants are alike in every age, and there is nothing in them inconſiſtent with propriety in God, or intereſt in the Covenant, or the Seal thereof, in one age more then in another: Baptiſm is the ſeal of the Covenant now, and may be adminiſtred to viſible Profeſſors, and their children, now, as Circumciſion was then; if there ſhould be any difference, Reaſon would tell us, conſidering the painfulneſs and peril of Circumciſion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.25. and the eaſineſs of Baptiſm, That only <hi>grown men</hi> ſhould have been circumciſed, and <hi>Infants</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, rather then contrary.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>ANABAPY. CAT. Q.</hi> Whether may not Infants of Believers be baptized by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Covenant-holineſs? <hi>A.</hi> No: for Baptiſm is not a ſign or ſeal of any ſuch outward holineſs, which may befall Reprobates as Well as Elect; but it is a ſign of Death, Burial, and Reſurrection, Which the Believerthath with Chriſt. <hi>2.</hi> There is no command for baptizing ſuch, if the Gentiles Were ſo holy.</head>
               <p>BAptiſm <hi>is a ſign and ſeal of Christs, Death,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Examinat. Cap. <hi>10. § 1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Burial, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,</hi> and of the truth and faithfulneſs of thoſe <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great and precious Promiſes</hi> bundled up in the Covenant of Grace, which are <hi>in Chriſt Yea and Amen,</hi> a <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. but it is not an abſolute ſign or ſeal of the baptized's <hi>Death, Burial, Reſurrection With Chriſt,</hi> of <hi>his putting on of Chriſt,</hi> of <hi>grace already Wrought</hi> in him, as you aſſert in your Anſwer to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and third queſtion, but only <hi>conditional, Acts</hi> 16.30 31. if he believe, as the <hi>Romans</hi> did, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3.4. with 5.1.2. A Chriſtian gathers the aſſurance of his Juſtification and Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by this or ſuch a like Syllogiſm, <hi>He that believeth, is juſtified, and ſhall be ſaved: I believe,</hi> therefore <hi>I am juſtified, and ſhall be ſaved.</hi> The Major, or former Propoſition, Baptiſm doth ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely and univerſally ſeal; but not ſo the Minor, or ſecond
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:44967:22"/>Propoſition, <hi>viz. I believe:</hi> If Baptiſm ſhould ſeal to all bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized ones, as ſuppoſe <hi>Simon Magus, Judas, &amp;c.</hi> the truth of their Faith and their ſaving intereſt in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> then ſhould God ſet his Seal (for Baptiſm is <hi>Gods Seal,</hi> not <hi>the Churches</hi>) to a lye and falſhood, or at leaſt command Miniſters ſo to do, when they are bound by the Rules of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to baptize ſuch as are not inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly holy, as <hi>Simon Magus, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Children of Believers,<note place="margin">ſect. 2.</note> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. are ſaid to be <hi>Saints,</hi> or <hi>holy;</hi> whereby is not meant, that they were <hi>legitimate</hi> only (for ſo had they been if both the Parents had been Infidels, and children are not <hi>holy</hi> becauſe they are not <hi>baſtards,</hi>) nor only <hi>ſanctified to the uſe of the Parents,</hi> as the unblieving yoke-fellow (though not holy <hi>in ſe,</hi> nor ſanctifying) is <hi>ſanctified to the believing yoke-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,</hi> (the Holy Ghoſt neither here nor elſewhere ſpeaking of any thing to be ſanctified to unbelievers,) but they are <hi>holy,</hi> a diſtinct phraſe from being <hi>ſanctified to another,</hi> as birds and beaſts may be, and this holineſs proceeds from the believing yoke-fellow, which is the reaſon why he ſaith, <hi>your</hi> children, <hi>viz the children of you Chriſtian yoke-fellows</hi> (the Infidel yoke fellows writ not to <hi>Paul</hi>) are <hi>holy,</hi> which ſeeing it cannot be meant of <hi>internal</hi> and ſaving holineſs (for all children of the Church are not ſuch, though we are bound to judg the beſt till the contrary appear,) it muſt needs therefore be meant of outward federal holineſs, which is the privl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the children of believing Parents above the children of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, the Jews having had the like priviledg before; (See <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 15. which I conceive runs parallel with this:) Or if but one of the Parents be Chriſtian, <hi>partus ſequitur meliorem partem,</hi> the children are not <hi>Infidels,</hi> but <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But,<note place="margin">§. 3.</note> ſay you, <hi>there is no command for baptizing ſuch,</hi> and you call it <hi>Will-worſhip</hi> forbidden, <hi>Lev.</hi> 10.1. <hi>A tradition and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work for more traditions;</hi> others call it <hi>the mark of the beaſt, one of the ſtrongeſt holds of Antichriſt,</hi> and what not? To all which I anſwer, 1. If <hi>Nadah and Abihu's offering ſtrange fire,</hi> fire un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanctified, or not taken off the Altar, <hi>Was Will-worſhip</hi> (though the Scripture doth not call it ſo,) yet Paedobaptiſm (ſuppoſe it be not warranted by the Word) cannot be will-worſhip, becauſe it is not an introduction of a new Worſhip or Ordinance, but the miſapplication of an old and unqueſtionable Ordinance of God, or (if you put on it the worſt name you can with any ſhew of reaſon)
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:44967:22"/>
                  <hi>the Profanation of an Ordinance,</hi> as your ſelf call it; ſome of your party, which have in deriſion and contempt of Infant-Baptiſm bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized Horſes, Cats, or Dogs, have been unqueſtionably guilty of horrible Profanation, but not of will-worſhip. 2. Infant-Baptiſm is grounded on, and warranted by the Word of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is far enough from being a Profanation, or ſo much as the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>application of an Ordinance: That it is ſo grounded and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted, needs no other proof then what hath already been produced in this Examination, upon occaſion of the Scriptures and Reaſons brought againſt it.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>They that are Diſciples in Scripture-ſence, are expreſſed in Chriſts Commiſſion about Baptiſm,</hi> and <hi>are to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed.</hi> But <hi>Infants of the Church are Diſciples in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-ſence:</hi> Therefore <hi>they are to be baptized.</hi> See Chap. 2. Sect. 3.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>They that are Abrahams ſeed are to be baptized,</hi> as you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs: But <hi>ſuch Infants are the ſeed of Abraham:</hi> Therefore <hi>they are to the baptized.</hi> See Chap. 7.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>They that are viſibly Within the Covenant of Grace are to be baptized,</hi> (as you acknowledg:) But <hi>ſuch Infants are viſibly Within the Covenant of Grace:</hi> Therefore <hi>they are to be baptized.</hi> See Chap. 8.</item>
                  <item>4. <hi>They that are to be judged Church-members are to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized:</hi> But <hi>ſuch Infants of the Church, or born of members of the Church are to be judged Church members:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>5. <hi>They of Whom the Kingdom of God is, are to partake of the privileges of the Kingdom of God;</hi> But <hi>of Infants is the Kingdom of God:</hi> Therefore &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>6. <hi>They that are Saints, and holy, are to be baptized:</hi> But <hi>ſuch Infants are Saints, and holy:</hi> Therefore.</item>
                  <item>7. <hi>Chriſt</hi> knew that Baptiſm was an ancient Ceremony of initi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation into the Church, and applyed to the Infants of the Church as well as to adult Proſelytes; yet he took up that Ceremony, and advanced it (as he did the <hi>Poſtcoenium</hi> of the Paſſover) to be a Sacrament of the New Teſtament, without prohibition of Infants from it; and therefore he did at leaſt approve, it ſhould be adminiſtred to Infants. See <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. § 1.</item>
               </list>
               <p>In theſe alone (to omit others,) conſcientious enquirers into the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:44967:23"/>mind of the Lord Jeſus may find ſatisfactory grounds of Infant-Baptiſm, eſpecially when they are compared with the grounds of the contrary Opinion and Practice.</p>
               <p>You cannot ſhew any precept at all,<note place="margin">§. 4.</note> or preſident, or good warrant, in the Word of God, that children of believing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents ſhould be kept from Baptiſm (as you require them to be) till they do in their own perſons actually believe, or make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith; or that any ſuch were baptized in riper years (as you would have them now to be:) Yea I further ſay, that if you can ſhew me in Scripture any ſon or daughter of believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Parents baptized, I ſhall ſhew you that he or ſhe was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in Infancy: Surely from the time that <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> begin his Miniſtry, to the writing of the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> great multitudes of Infants of Chriſtians grew up to maturity, yet amongſt them all we read not of one whoſe Baptiſm was ſo delayed; nor have we any ſolid ground to conceive, that God at the coming of Chriſt took away Infants Covenant intereſt, Church member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Sacramental initiation, and made their condition (as to this) as bad as the Heathen, and worſe then the Jewiſh chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſeeing it cannot be ſaid, that God did take theſe priviledges away <hi>in judgment,</hi> upon occaſion of Chriſts coming, from all Infants, even Elect children of Elect Parents, ſeeing Infants in the time of the Goſpel are not any way more guilty, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable, then in former times: nor can it any way appear, that God did it <hi>in mercy,</hi> (and ſure if it was done, it was done either <hi>in judgment</hi> or <hi>mercy,</hi>) for it was a mercy to the Jewiſh chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to have theſe priviledges, and nothing more was conferred upon Infants which loſt them, then upon adult Chriſtians which did not loſe them. You cannot ſhew a precept' or preſident for your gathering Churches out of other true Chriſtian Churches; for requiring perſons, before they can be admitted members, to give account of the truth of their graces; for the Congregations judging whether they have grace or no, and conſequently whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were to be admitted or no; for a ſolemn explicite Church-Covenant, for the erection of a Church without Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers; for the power of ſuch a Church, conſiſting only of unof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed Chriſtians, to elect, ordain, impoſe hands by one or more of them on their Officers, to cenſure or excommunicate any member, yea any or all their Officers when they have them;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:44967:23"/>for maintenance of Miniſters by Lords. Day-Collections, formerly urged as an Ordinance of God, though of late much waved; for a ſentence of non-communion with Siſter-Churches; for Synods only conſultative, and not decretive; for publike ordinary preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of gifted men, not ſo much as intending the Miniſtry, and their receiving maintenance for their pains; and yet theſe are aſſerted by men of the Congregational way (in which <hi>Antipaedobaptists</hi> are generally found) to be duties, priviledges of the Church, or Ordinances of God: nor can you ſhew any Church conſiſting of unbaptized ones (ſuch as you account your ſelves to be (your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm being a nullity) till you be baptized upon profeſſion) und ſuch a Church admitting members, commiſſionating ſome Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to preach and dip: nor any precept or preſident for admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch, which are (in your opinion) unbaptized, to the Lords Supper, not for rebaptizing ſuch as were <hi>baptized</hi> (ſuppoſe in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy) <hi>in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt,</hi> or for renouncing ſuch Baptiſm: nor can you ſhew any one Text of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in which Infant-Baptiſm either in expreſs words, or in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of any Apoſtolick or Primitive Church or Father in the pureſt Times: nor can you ſhew one viſible Church, from the beginning of the World, to the time when your Opinion was lately broached, which was of any long continuance, and did nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther admit into it, nor permit in it, any Infant-member.</p>
               <p>Finally,<note place="margin">§. 5.</note> Should you or I be required a <hi>Command</hi> for admiſſion of women to the Supper (as you require a <hi>Command for Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> though you can neither ſhew command, nor example nor good warrant for your contrary opinions and practices,) what clearer command can we ſhew for that, then for Infant-Baptiſm? Women were not admitted to both the Sacraments of the Old Teſtament: Chriſt did not admit women, no not his own Mother, to the Supper: There is expreſs uncontroverted mention in the New Teſtament of women being baptized, but not ſo of women communicating. If you alledg, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (a name common to women, as well as m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n) ought to communicate, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. it is early evaded, by ſaying, that the Apoſtle confines it to the Male by <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>v.</hi> 28, 29. and the ſame word is uſed of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, of which the Male only was capable, <hi>Joh</hi> 7.22. General terms of Diſciples, Church-members, perſons in Covenant, will carry it for Infants Baptiſm, as well as womens communicating:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:44967:24"/>If you alledg, That ſuch and ſuch Aſſemblies, in which there were women, did break bread, you know it may be, yea it is doubted by ſome ſober ſpirits, whether that breaking of bread was Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal or no; and it may be ſaid, that the company is ſaid to do it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Males did it; as the whole houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is ſaid to be circumciſed, and called <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> though the Females thereof were not circumciſed. If you ſhould tell us of houſholds admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Supper (though I know not any ſuch inſtance in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) I might as well ſay, there was no women there, or they were excluded, as you ſay, there was no Infants in ſuch or ſuch an houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, or if there were, they were excluded. Laſtly, If men ſhould bend their ſtrength that way, they might as plauſibly except againſt your admiſſion of women (uſually the forwardeſt part of your Societies) to the Supper, as you do, or (I believe) can do againſt Paedobaptiſm. Oh that our good God would in mercy to this diſtracted Church, and to the deluded Souls therein, remove preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice out of our hearts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>ANABAPT. CAT.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whether do you think Baptiſm adminiſtred in Infancy to be a lawful Baptiſm, and ſufficient?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. <hi>To me it is not; for I think it to be a Profanation of an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, for theſe Reaſons:</hi> 1. <hi>Becauſe it is taught by the precepts of men,</hi> Iſai. 29.13. <hi>not by God,</hi> Jerem. 7.22, 23.</p>
               <p>YOu hold,<note place="margin">Exam. Chap. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> it ſeems, that <hi>it is neither lawful nor ſufficient,</hi> and (in plain Engliſh) it is <hi>null,</hi> voyd, no Baptiſm at all: But conſider (I pray you) could you prove the nullity of Infant-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm (as you have a great mind to do) what ſad conſequences would enſue: 1. That the people of God, for the ſpace of 1600 years uſing Paedobaptiſm, were deſtitute of <hi>one,</hi> if not (by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence) of <hi>both</hi> the Sacraments. 2. That the Churches in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland, France, Denmark, Sweden, Germany, Geneva, Holland, New England, &amp;c.</hi> which have uſually no other Baptiſm but Child-Baptiſm, are no Churches, the members thereof being not ſo much as Chriſtians outwardly, nor Sacramentally initiated into the Church; in doing whereof you diſhonor God, and do Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:44967:24"/>great ſervice, Gods work being to <hi>diſciple and enchirch the Nations of the World, Matt.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. and <hi>Satan's</hi> to <hi>undeſciple and He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thenize the Church,</hi> either in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, or in reputation, for the advancement of his own Kingdom. 3. That theſe, and all others, muſt for ever (as the caſe ſtands) want the Sacrament of Baptiſm, except a ſpecial and particular warrant come from Heaven (as to <hi>John Baptiſt</hi>) for the ſetting up of this Ordinance; for no man, who is both unſeparated to the work of the Miniſtry, and unbaptized (his Paedobaptiſm being a nullity) and ununited to the Church of Chriſt, can warrantably baptize himſelf, or any other, any more then <hi>Saul</hi> might ſacrifice, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> ſtay the Ark, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> offer Incenſe; a Midwife, <hi>Turk, Jew</hi> or <hi>Pagan</hi> adminiſter the Sacraments of Chriſts Church: for if Paedobaptiſm be a nullity becauſe of default in the ſubject, this alſo will be a nullity for want of commiſſion; for you can ſhew neither precept, preſident, nor good warrant for the Word, for any man that is unbaptized (having no ſpecial Commiſſion from God) to baptize himſelf, or to baptize any other; or for any man to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of Baptiſm from ſuch an one, which is indeed no Baptiſm at all. <hi>John,</hi> as he had commiſſion from God for his baptizing; ſo he affirms, that <hi>a man can receive nothing</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> no authority to baptize as he did) <hi>except it be given him from Heaven, John</hi> 3. 26, 27. as if he would profeſſedly caution the Church againſt ſuch courſes. 4. That the Societies of the <hi>Independents</hi> and <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists</hi> (notwithſtanding their ſeparation from us) do yet (except they alſo turn <hi>Anabaptists</hi>) live within one of <hi>the ſtrongeſt holds of Antichriſt,</hi> are guilty of <hi>obſerving traditions</hi> and <hi>precepts of men,</hi> of <hi>will-worſhip,</hi> of <hi>profanation of Gods holy Ordinance,</hi> of <hi>filling the Church with rotten members,</hi> of <hi>confounding the Church and the World together;</hi> yea (ſay ſome of you) they <hi>have the mark of the Beaſt</hi> in their ſoreheads, and by conſequence are in the high way to eternal damnation: And what worſe can you ſay of any? Your Texts prove, that God hates hypocriſie, and over much regard of the commandments of men, and that God did command Obedience rather then Sacriſice, as 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.22. (for God did command Sacrifices and Offerings, <hi>Levit.</hi> chap. 1. 2.3. &amp;c.) What is this to Paedobaptiſm Will you acknowledg that God hath commanded it to us, as he did burnt-offerings and ſacrifices to the Jews? we our ſelves ſay no more for it: But if
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:44967:25"/>your Texts do forbid all humane inventions in the Worſhip of God, Paedobaptiſm is yet ſafe enough; for it hath been proved in the foregoing Chapter to have as good warrant from the Word, as ſome other (by your ſelf acknowledged) Ordinances of God have, and better then your oppoſite Opinion and Practicas.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>ANABAPT. CAT.</head>
               <p>A. <hi>Paedobaptiſm is done in a Wrong manner, by ſprinkling in ſtead of Dipping.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THis exception you begin your Catechiſun with, telling us, that <hi>Baptiſm ſignifies Dipping;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Examinat. Chap. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>By Dipping is never ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Sprinkling:</hi> whence you would infer, That <hi>Baptiſm ſhould be by Dipping</hi> only, and that <hi>it is done in a Wrong manner When it is done by Sprinkling;</hi> wherein you much miſtake: For. 1. Should the original ſignification of other Scriptures words be ſo much ſqueezed, then becauſe the holy Communion is call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d a <hi>Supper,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20. (the word ſignifying a whole meal,) and the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. ſignifies not ſimply to <hi>ſing,</hi> but to <hi>ſing to a muſical Inſtrument,</hi> and the original words for the geſture at the Supper ſignifie <hi>lying</hi> or <hi>leaning on a bed;</hi> you might with as good reaſon collect, <hi>That the holy Communion ſhould be a whole meal.</hi> That <hi>there ſhould be inſtrumental muſick in Churches</hi> as well as vocal, That <hi>men ought to lie or lean on beds</hi> at the receiving of the Supper, or <hi>elſe the Ordinances are dons in a Wrong manner.</hi> 2 The word <hi>Baptiſm</hi> by your own confeſſion doth ſignifie <hi>waſhing</hi> as well as <hi>dipping,</hi> and waſhing is the main thing, being the <hi>end,</hi> and dipping but the <hi>means,</hi> eſpecially with reference to this Ordinance, which is for <hi>waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or putting away the filth of the fleſh,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Acts</hi> 22.16. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.22. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. Now a thing may be waſhed, not only by Dipping, but by Sprinkling, or by affuſion or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing water upon it, which is moſtly uſed by us, and not Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. 3. The Greek word <hi>Baptiſm</hi> in Scripture ſignifie, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly waſhing by dipping or plunging into the water, but by ſprinkling or affuſion. The <hi>Baptiſms,</hi> or waſhings, mentioned <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.10. were (at leaſt ſome of them) done onely by
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:44967:25"/>
                  <hi>ſprinkling of water, Numb.</hi> 8.7. which was called the <hi>water of ſeparation, Numb.</hi> 19.9. and <hi>holy water, Numb.</hi> 5.17. or by <hi>ſprinkling of blood,</hi> which himſelf inſtanceth in, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.13, 19, 21. See alſo <hi>Exod.</hi> 29.16, 21. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.7. Their waſhings (called <hi>baptizings</hi>) of hands, were frequently (at leaſt) by letting wate fall on their hands from a Laver, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 3.11. So their Tables and Beds were not dipped into the water, but waſhing with pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing water on them, <hi>Mark</hi> 9. They that were <hi>baptized with the Holy Ghoſt, and with fire,</hi> were not dipped or plunged into the fire, (though, if they had, if ſeems it would not have burned them,) but <hi>cloven tongues, as of fire, ſat upon each of them, Acts</hi> 2.3. with <hi>Matt.</hi> 3.11. They that were <hi>baptized in the Cloud, and in the Sea,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1. were not dipped or plunged into the Cloud or Sea, for it was dry Land; but probably they were bedewed, beſprinkled, or dropped on. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>baptized,</hi> (by the Tranſlation rendered <hi>dipt</hi>) <hi>Revel.</hi> 19.13. is no other in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 63.2, 3. then <hi>besprinkled.</hi> 4. Baptiſm ſignifies <hi>Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the blood</hi> of Chriſt, which is called the <hi>Blood of Sprinkling, Hebr.</hi> 12.24. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.22. and <hi>Sanctification by the Spirit</hi> of Chriſt, which is called <hi>ſprinkling of clean water on them, Ezek.</hi> 36.25. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 52.15. both which were alſo typified by the aforeſaid legal purifications or waſhings. 5. It cannot be proved by the Word, nor is it probable in it ſelf, that the three thouſand baptized in <hi>Jeruſalem, Acts</hi> 2.41. were carryed to a River, and there dipped one by one by the Apoſtles; or that <hi>Paul, Lydia,</hi> the Jaylor, and all theirs, which (it's likely) were bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in houſes, were ſo dipped. Did they ſhift their clothes, or continued they in their wet apparel? and how could their whole body be waſhed (though it might be wet) with their clothes on? or were they all (men and women) baptized ſtark naked? and was not this contrary to modeſty, and a temptation which maſtered holy <hi>David?</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.1. Much leſs can it be proved, that be the perſon never ſo ſickly, the ſeaſon never ſo cold, yet dipping is (though it may endanger mens lives) not only lawful in it ſelf, (as we account it, yea it hath been commended above ſprinkling or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion,) but in all caſes and conditions neceſſary, and the omiſſion of it upon any occaſion is ſinful.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:44967:26"/>
               <head>ANABAPT. CAT.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paedobaptiſm is done by an Officer, where there is a question<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Power, as the Ministers ordained by Biſhops deem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Antichristian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THis exception is of no force againſt Child Baptiſm adminiſtred by ſuch Miniſters as are not ordained by Biſhops.<note place="margin">Exam. Cap. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> 2. You tell us not by whom, or whether <hi>truly</hi> or <hi>falſly</hi> the Biſhops were deemed Antichriſtian: certes the old Nonconformiſts (how ever they or ſome of them might hold, that in the calling and authority of the Biſhops there be divers things Antichriſtian,) agreed by joynt conſent, <hi>That they did not ſee</hi> (I uſe their own words) <hi>how our Biſhops could be called Antichrists, or Antichriſtians:</hi> 1. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Word marks out Antichriſt by his falſe doctrine; nor do we find in holy Scripture any ſuch accounted Antichriſt, or Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, which holding the truth of Doctrine, ſwerveth either in judgment or practice from Chriſts rule for Diſcipline: now it is evident that our Biſhops do hold and teach all fundamental Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines and Truths, and ſome of them have ſoundly maintained it againſt Hereticks, converted many to it, and have ſuffered perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution for the Gospel.</hi> 2. <hi>Their Hierarchy and other corruptions charged upon the calling of our Biſhops, were rather to be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſtairs and way to Antichriſtianity, then Antichriſtianity it ſelf; for they were in the Church before the Pope, who is the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, and the chief Head-link of all Antichriſtianity, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed.</hi> 3. <hi>The Antichristian Biſhops hold their preeminence as from Gods Law, which is unchangeable; whereas our Biſhops, ſince her Majeſties reign to this day (for the moſt part) held their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority by no other right then the poſitive Law, which is vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; yea it appears by the Inſtitution of the Court of Delegates, and the continuance thereof to this day, that they do and ought by Law to hold their Juriſdiction, not as from God, but as from the Prince.</hi> Thus they. And as to Miniſters ordained by the Biſhops, they ſay, <hi>Biſhops are able to judg of ſuch gifts as are required for the ſufficiency of Miniſters, that many of them have been ſuch Miniſters themſelves, as to Whoſe labors the Lord hath ſet to his Seal—We are perſwaded, that (though it were not neceſſary, yet) it cannot be unlawful for him that entreth into the Miniſtry to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:44967:26"/>be approved and authorized even by them. And if our Ordination be in this behalf faulty, how will our Brethren juſtifie the calling of their own Miniſters, that have received Ordination ever from the people, who neither by commandment nor example can be found to have any ſuch authority, nor are in any degree ſo capable of it, as the Biſhops?</hi> See Mr <hi>Rathbands</hi> grave Confutation, &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 19. and 38. 3. Suppoſe it were confeſſed, That the Biſhops, as claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Gods Law ſole power of Ordination and Juriſdiction (if any ſo did) might in ſome qualified ſence be called Antichriſtian; had this ſuch an influence upon an Ordination, in which others joyned as well as he, ſo as to make it voyd and null, both as from himſelf, and from them? The Biſhops were Presbyters, and ſo more enabled by Gods Word to ordain (as the godly Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts truly aſſert) then any Non-Presbyters; and they came nearer to <hi>a Preſbytery</hi> then two, three, or more members (which are nothing like a Presbytery, or company of Presbyters) can do: and their Ordination was judged valid, not only by the Parliament and the Aſſembly, but alſo by all the Reformed Churches abroad, as by the Nonconformiſts at home, notwithſtanding they were oppoſers of, and were oppoſed by the Biſhops; yea, God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf added his own Seal, affording not only Miniſterial Gifts and Graces, but his gracious aſſiſtance, for Converſion of Souls, and edifying of the Saints; and (ſometimes) ſo gloriouſly working by the Miniſtry of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as he hath not (that we know of) wrought ſo by any other. But in your account the <hi>Baptiſm adminiſtred</hi> by ſuch a Miniſter <hi>is neither lawful nor ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient,</hi> or at leaſt it is the <hi>profanation of the Ordinance:</hi> Who you are, I know not; but the general Opinion of your party is, that any <hi>Diſciple</hi> (eſpecially a <hi>teaching Diſciple</hi>) <hi>may baptize:</hi> (See <hi>Confeſſion of the ſeven Churches,</hi> Art. 41.) And doth Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation by a Biſhop, and other Miniſters, make voyd ſuch Diſciple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and make him that he cannot be ſo much as a private Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, yea make his Baptiſm Antichriſtian? We receive from God the Old Teſtament by the hands of the Jews, and the whole Bible by the hands of Papiſts; moſt Scriptures have ſome time or other been abuſed, muſt we therefore diſuſe them? If a Biſhop ſhould baptize one at full age, making profeſſion of faith and repentance, yea ſuppoſe a Jeſuite, pretending to be a gifted Brother, or a teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſciple, (as it is lawful for the Jeſuites to ſay or do any thing
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:44967:27"/>that may tend to the weakening the true Reformed Religion,) and ſhould dip many, would his dipping be null and voyd, and to be reiterated? This I dare ſay, Whatſoever is rational or religious, cannot be made irrational or irreligious, whoſoever uſeth or hath uſed it: And if multitudes of perſons ſhould caſt away all that they have received by the Biſhops and Miniſters ordained by them, they ſhould with thoſe things irrecoverably caſt their Souls into Hell. When Antichriſt moſt reigned and raged, and the woman fled into the Wilderneſs, God did preſerve ſome Fundamental Doctrines, and the eſſence of Baptiſm, and the eſſence of a true Miniſtry diſpenſing it; and <hi>they,</hi> that is, her Paſtors, <hi>did feed her there, Revel.</hi> 12.6, 14. 4. There are now more Antichriſts, then ever were before in our, or in any other Reformed Church; and worſe Antichriſts, by how much Fundamental Errors in Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine are greater abominations then Errors only in Diſcipline: All Heretiques in Scripture-language are Antichriſt, 1 <hi>Epiſt. John.</hi> The Errors, Hereſies, Blaſphemies, Treacheries, Hypocriſies, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, ſacrilegious ſeditious Actions, Diviſions and Subdiviſions, bitter and bloody Contentions, Rebaptizations, Ordinations by the people, and other meer humane inventions of theſe Times, do juſtifie the Biſhops, and all Epiſcopal men (that have kept them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves free from theſe and the like crimes) from being ſo Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian as we; do really diſhonor the true Reformed Religion, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light the truly Antichriſtian Faction, and make way for our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing, not only to Prelacy, but to that which all ſober men count incomparably more dangerous, to Popery, yea to the worſt editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> Jeſuited, Inquiſition-Popery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>ANABAPT. CAT.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paedobaptiſm is done upon a wrong ſubject, who is not in Chriſts commiſſion,</hi> Matt. 28.19. <hi>nor</hi> Mark 16.16. <hi>Believers and Repentants being the ſubjects therein.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>EXAMINAT.</p>
               <p>You here beg the queſtion; what you here alledg, hath been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:44967:27"/>
               <head>ANABAPT. CAT.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>All the certainty I can have of ſuch a Baptiſm, is only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectural, not infallible; whereas the outward ſign of a Sacrament muſt be viſible and infallible, as the thing ſignified is; this Infant-Baptiſm I take only in truſt from others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THe Infants bleſſed by <hi>Chriſt</hi> could in their riper age have no certainty of their being ſo bleſſed by him,<note place="margin">Examinat. Chap. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> nor had the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Infants any certainty of their Circumciſion; for the foreskin of circumciſed Infants might be, and ſometimes was, ſo drawn up, that when they came to age they could not diſcern their Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion. To this <hi>Paul</hi> alludes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.18. If the fleſh-mark was alway diſcernable, yet it could not teach them whether a friend or foe had done it, whether for ſacred or civil ends, whether duly or unduly, without inſtruction and information by word or writing; and ſuch inſtruction may aſſure us of our right Baptiſm, though it was adminiſtred in Infancy. You may have ſuch aſſurance of your Baptiſm, as the Prieſts by the <hi>Regiſters</hi> had of their pedigree, <hi>Ez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> 2.62. as <hi>Paul</hi> had, that he was circumciſed the eighth day, that he was of the <hi>ſtock of Iſrael, an Hebrew of the Hebrews, of the tribe of Benjamin, Phil.</hi> 3.5. Yea, you may have as much or more certainty that you were baptized, as that ſuch an one was your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſuch a woman your mother: yet ſure (if you will call that only a conjectural and not infallible teſtimony) you will teſt ſo much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, as to call him your father, and her your mother, that are teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and reputed to be ſo, and without ſcruple of conſcience honor them, as you are bound by the fifth Commandment; and alſo keep that which is generally computed to be the firſt day of the week, or the Lords-Day, though you take it but on truſt from others: Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly he that is baptized at full age, may not infallibly know that he was baptized; ſome have forgotten (through ſickneſs) the greateſt concernments, yea their own names, muſt they thereupon be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptized? Poſſibly a man or woman, as you are dipping them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the water, may be ſo damped, that they may not hear, or not heed the words uſed by the Adminiſtrator, whether he baptize, or bleſs, or curſe; muſt they be dipped again, till they do hear, and heed, that they may infallibly know themſelves to be baptized?
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:44967:28"/>If a man ſhould herein be deceived, and think he was baptized in his Infancy, when he was not, the Error is not very dangerous; Faith in Chriſt may ſupply the defect of Baptiſm: and he not neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting or contemning Baptiſm, nor knowing that he wants it, may reap benefit by his ſuppoſed Baptiſm, as if it were re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l.</p>
               <p>As for his reſolution of the caſe (grounded on the ſuppoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulneſs of Paedobaptiſm,) <hi>whether a Chriſtian may with good conſcience be preſent at it,</hi> I judg it unneceſſary for me to diſcuſs it, (having (I hope) cleared the lawfulneſs of Infant-Baptiſm,) yet I confeſs, I cannot approve ſundry things in it, though Paedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſm were confeſſed to be unlawful.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:44967:28"/>
            <head>SOME OBSERVATIONS Both Old and New, Concerning the pretended Viſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Univerſality, Antiquity, Infallibility, Unity and Purity of the preſent <hi>Roman</hi> Church and Religion.</head>
            <head type="sub">Sent to a Gentleman upon his Revolt to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery; and now Publiſhed (with ſome few Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) for the Churches good.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">1. YOu do all confeſs the affirmative and poſitive Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines of the Church of <hi>England</hi> and other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches to be true and Catholique, and to have had viſible Profeſſors in all Ages; only you ſuperadd certain other Doctrines, which (you ſay) are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be beleeved unto Salvation:</p>
            <p>For evidence whereof, obſerve,</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. Our Churches Doctrine, All the Books of the Old and New Teſtament, mentioned in the 39 Articles, and in the late Confeſſion of Faith, to be holy and Canonical, are for ſuch to be received.</cell>
                     <cell>2. Your Churches Additions. <hi>The Books of Tobit, Judeth, Wiſdom, Maccabees, and the reſt (commonly called Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha) are alſo Canonical.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Scripture is the Rule of Faith and Manners.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Traditions of the Church are of equal Authority with the Scriptures.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:44967:29"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Originals, Hebrew and Greek, are Authentical.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Vulgar Edition is moſt pure and Authentical.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>There are two Sacraments of the New Teſtament; Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and the Lords Supper.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>There are alſo five more,</hi> viz. <hi>Confirmation, Pennance, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction, Orders (of which there are ſeven,</hi> viz. <hi>Prieſts, Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, Sub-deacons, Acolytes, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orciſts, Lectors or Readers, Oſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries or Door-keepers) and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>God is to be invocated, and Religiouſly worſhipped.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yea, and the Images of God alſo, Croſſes, Crucifixes, Altars, Angels, Saints, with their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques and Images.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Chriſt is the Head of the Church.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>And the Pope alſo.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Chriſt is our Mediator and Advocate.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>So are the Angels and Saints likewiſe.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Chriſt was conceived with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out original ſin.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>And the Virgin Mary alſo.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Chriſt was once ſacrificed on the Croſs for the Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Chriſt is dayly offered up in Maſs a propitiatory Sacrifice for the ſins of quick and dead.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>We are ſaved by the merits of Chriſt.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>And alſo by the merits of the Saints.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>We are juſtified by Faith.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>And by hope, love fear of God, good works, which merit Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>All the words and actions which Scripture records to be uſed by Chriſt in the celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Supper, are to be uſed by us alſo.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The ſacred Hoaſt muſt alſo be elevated, adored reſerved, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in ſolemn proceſſion.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Chriſt is truly preſent in the Euchariſt.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Chriſt is corporally preſent by Tranſubſtantiation, and may be received into the mouths of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, yea of Rats and Mice.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>There are two places for the Souls of ſuch as depart hence.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>And two beſides,</hi> viz. <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory and Limbus Infantum.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:44967:29"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The three Creeds, common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called the Creed of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Councel, and of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and beleeved.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>And Pope</hi> Pius <hi>his Creed alſo, or his additions to the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene Creed, are alſo to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and beleeved.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe and the like poſitive Points of the Reformed Religion (whereof I omit ſundry) are truly and properly Catholique, for in them not only Papiſts, but in a manner all Chriſtians in the world concur with us: but in your Additions you ſtand ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, and have multitudes of Chriſtians in the Eaſtern and Weſtern Churches diſſenting from you.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Peruſe the Book of nine and thirty Articles, the Homilies, Leiturgy and Catechiſms, or the late Directory, Confeſſion of Faith, or Catechiſms, larger or ſhorter, and find if you can the Doctrine of our Church contrary to any one Article of thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Creeds which in the firſt ſix hundred years were Badges of Catholique Profeſſion, or produce any one of thoſe Articles to which we do not willingly ſubſcribe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though the ancient Church did undoubtedly beleeve and profeſs all that was neceſſary to Salvation, yet there is not one Creed of General or National Counced, particular Church or Father, within a thouſand or twelve hundred years after Chriſt, in which the Articles of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> his Creed were impoſed (as now they are) for Articles of Faith neceſſary to be beleeved un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Salvation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Church of God (as might be proved by Scriptures or Fathers, if it were not acknowledged by your own Authors) cannot make a new Article of Faith, nor any addition to the Creed, ſave by way of Explication of that which was formerly upon Scripture grounds beleeved and profeſſed: But theſe addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of yours were not beleeved (if you ſhould ſay that they were beleeved <hi>implicitely,</hi> this (ſuppoſe it true) would take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Viſibility of the Profeſſion thereof) by the Ancient Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>holique and Apoſtolique Church.</p>
            <p n="5">5. None of your ſide hitherto hath, or hereafter can produce any one viſible Church, which in the Apoſtolique and in all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Ages did approve and uſe Communion in one kind, Private Maſs, Prayer in an unknown Tongue, Image-worſhip,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:44967:30"/>Pardons, Indulgences, which beleeved the Popes Infallibility, his Superiority over General Councels, his temporal Authority over Kings and Emperors to depoſe them, and diſpoſe of their Dominions, the neceſſity of auricular Confeſſion, the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate number of ſeven Sacraments, Purgatory, and the Popes Power to deliver Souls from thence, which forbade Lay-men (without a ſpecial diſpenſation) to read the Scriptures, or Prieſts to marry, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Nay you cannot name any one perſon in each ſeveral Age, out of whoſe words or writings (notwithſtanding there were ſundry Creeds, Confeſſions of Faith, Catechiſms, Sermons or Homilies, Summaries of Chriſtian Doctrine) the aforeſaid par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Points of Popery may be collected, deſcending from the age of <hi>Christ</hi> to the days of <hi>Luther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Nay you cannot name any one Father or Catholique Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for twelve hundred years after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that did hold all thoſe Tenets which are now taught by the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized by the <hi>Trent</hi> Councel.</p>
            <p n="8">8. None of your ſide hath or can prove, that any of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Martyrs or Confeſſors ſuffered Death, Baniſhment, Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Confiſcation, &amp;c. for the Popiſh Religion, or any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar thereof, in which they differ from the Church of <hi>England;</hi> as Papal Supremacy, Communion in one kind, Image-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="9">9. You cannot ſhew, that any one Article of your Faith in which we diſſent from you, is Catholique according to <hi>Vincen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Lirinenſis</hi> his Rules, <hi>viz.</hi> which was Ancient in his time, and in reſpect of the <hi>Arrian</hi> Hereſie, which he calls <hi>novellum dogma, a novel tenet;</hi> and that which you know, that not <hi>unus aut duo tantum ſed omnes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>not only one or two, but all, though living in ſeveral times and places, have with one conſent openly, frequently, conſtantly held written and taught.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. None of your ſide dare for ſhame affirm, that Communion in both kinds, Prayer in a known Tongue, communion of Prieſt with people, Lay-mens reading of the Scriptures, Worſhip of God without Images, Invocation of God without mediation of Saints or Angels, and other the aforeſaid affirmative and poſitive Doctrines, were invented by <hi>Luther,</hi> or that they are not in themſelves ſo lawful and agreeable to the Scriptures, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:44967:30"/>practiſe of the firſt ſix centuries of years, as Communion in one kind, Prayer in an unknown Tongue, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="11">11. There are few or no Points denyed or affirmed againſt us by you, in which you vary not amongſt your ſelves; and if any of you will diſtinctly ſet down (avoyding general and ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous terms) what he thinketh to be the truth in any Queſtion or Expoſition of Scripture controverted betwixt us, I verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve I can name him another Papiſt, new or old, that ſaith the contrary: <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth <hi>obiter</hi> diſcover to the world above three hundred ſeveral Opinions of Papiſts, and thoſe only in and about the Points controverted between you and us; and <hi>Nava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> mentions about ſixty Diſſentions of your Doctors in one only Point, to wit, Confeſſion.</p>
            <p n="12">12. I ſhall hold, till herein I be convinced of Error by inſtance to the contrary, that whatſoever titles are by the ancient Fathers given to the Euchariſt, whereby you would prove Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, Adoration, Sacrifice, &amp;c. the ſame phraſes, or ſome equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to them, may be found in the Fathers concerning Baptiſm, in which you confeſs there is neither Tranſubſtantiation nor Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Alſo, that thoſe glorious things which were ſpoken by them of the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> may be parallel'd by ſuch as read them throughly with the like honorable mention of other Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs and Biſhops.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Alſo, that as good teſtimony may be produced out of the Fathers for the abſolute neceſſity of the Euchariſt, as for the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute neceſſity of Baptiſm.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Alſo, that though <hi>gemina</hi> or <hi>duo Sacramenta</hi> be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times found, yet <hi>ſeptem Sacramenta,</hi> or words equivalent to them, cannot be found in any ancient Father, though they did call by the name of Sacraments, not only Ordination, Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, &amp;c. but ablution of the feet, ſign of the Croſs, &amp;c. which are not properly ſo called.</p>
            <p n="16">16. I deſire to be ſatisfied why you ſo frequently and ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly (the matter being ſo mainly controverted) do in your allowed Manuals, Catechiſms, &amp;c. leave out of the Decalogue all the ſecond Commandment, or that large paſſage prohibiting the worſhip of Images.</p>
            <p n="17">17. Alſo, how you can reconcile the two Bibles of <hi>Sixtus</hi> and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:44967:31"/>
               <hi>Clement,</hi> between which are ſo many and material differences; or if you cannot reconcile them, how you can ſatisfie your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience whether of them is Authentical, ſeeing they have equal Authority from the See Apoſtolique, equal Abſolutions from Oaths of admitting any other, equal Imprecations and Curſes to them which receive them not for Authentical; ſo that either you muſt uſe no Bible at all, or undergo the curſe of Pope <hi>Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> if you uſe that of <hi>Clement;</hi> or of Pope <hi>Clement,</hi> if you uſe the other of <hi>Sixtus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. For as much as Traditions are defined to be the Rule of Faith, and equal to the Scriptures, and nothing is more neceſſary for the Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch to do then to deliver the Rule of Faith clearly and preciſely; what is the cauſe I pray you, that no Pope or Councel, no not that of <hi>Trent,</hi> hath given an exact Catalogue or Liſt of divine and infallible Traditions? is it becauſe you are not fully as yet agreed of them, or are they for ſome politique ends reſerved in the Popes Breſt?</p>
            <p n="19">19. This Aſſertion [that <hi>the Roman Church is infallible in all her Decrees and Definitions</hi>] is the Foundation of your Faith, and if it fail, your Faith fails alſo; yet it is much doubted of, yea denyed by ſome Romaniſts; nor (as I ſuppoſe) was it ever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clated, decreed or defined by the Church in any General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel; if it was, I pray you ſhew me when, where, and in what terms.</p>
            <p n="20">20. Suppoſe this was ſo defined, and thereupon you be aſſured that the Church is infallible, yet you cannot be infallibly aſſured what is meant by the Church, which ſome of your Doctors in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret to be the Church <hi>eſſential,</hi> ſome the Church <hi>repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> (which, as ſome of them hold, is a General Councel, though without the Pope; others, the Councel and the Pope together,) ſome the Church <hi>virtual,</hi> the Pope alone; which yet are not agreed amongſt themſelves when, where, and in what matters the Pope may or may not err.</p>
            <p n="21">21. If herein you were reſolved, yet you cannot be infallibly aſſured that the preſent Pope is a true and lawful Pope, ſeeing he may be promoted by Simony, or his Baptizer or Ordainer, or the Baptizers or Ordainers of them, or ſome of them, might miſs the right intention of Baptizing or Ordaining, in which caſe he cannot be in the ſight of God a lawful Pope.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:44967:31"/>
            <p n="22">22. Put caſe you hope well of your Pope, yet it is poſſible you may miſtake Papal Decrees, Definitions, &amp;c. and not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them in their true and genuine ſence. <hi>Soto</hi> and <hi>Catharinus,</hi> who were preſent at the <hi>Trent</hi> Councel, could not agree what was the Councels meaning in the Points of Original Sin and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, but writ Books one againſt another of that Subject.</p>
            <p n="23">23. You will ſay perhaps, The Pope is a living Judg to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine theſe or the like doubts; which if it were granted, yet ſtill you have no ſuch infallible certainty as you pretend; for you never heard the Pope preach, propound Truths, or reſolve Doubts; you only hear his Prieſts and Jeſuits, whom I hope you will not exempt from a poſſibility of deceiving, or being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, eſpecially ſeeing both Prieſts and Jeſuits, Dominicans and Franciſcans, do pretend the Pope to be their Patron, and their Tenents, though contrary one to another, to be the Tenents of the Church.</p>
            <p n="24">24. Laſtly (to omit other Obſervations till further occaſion) If proof of the Churches Infallibility be demanded of you, you will alledg <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.18. or <hi>Luke</hi> 22.32. or ſome other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. If again you be demanded, what aſſutance you have that <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.18. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.32. and the other Scriptures, are of divine Authority, and that they are not corrupted nor miſ interpreted? you muſt anſwer, That the Church is infallible, which keeps and interprets the Scripture. Thus you prove the Infallibility of the Church by the Scriptures, and the Infallibility of the Scriptures by the Church, which is nothing elſe but to run round in a circle to beg the Queſtion, and in effect to prove the Churches Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility by the Infallibility of the Church.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur, <hi>Edm: Calamy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>March</hi> 4. 1652.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
